<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Philosophy | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/blog/categories/philosophy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-21T21:06:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://yoursite.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mental State Theory: An Inadequate Picture of Happiness]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2013/04/mental-state-theory-an-inadequate-picture-of-happiness/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2013/04/mental-state-theory-an-inadequate-picture-of-happiness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>In investigating questions of human happiness, it’s important to explore the very concept of happiness itself. Unfortunately, this word is used in myriad contexts and comes loaded with many meanings. For the purposes of this article, I will use the term to refer to the deeper type of happiness that we associate with human flourishing — the type of happiness we mean when we ask ourselves the question, “Am I <em>really</em> happy?”</p>

<p>Questioning this type of happiness itself will hopefully bring into focus a better picture of the nature of happiness and its role in human flourishing, as well as introduce important questions that must be addressed in giving an adequate account of happiness. Though I acknowledge the fact that happiness has an inescapably subjective nature — after all, each of us is made happy by different things — I think we can still hold meaningful discussions about the objective aspects of happiness, namely, what it is that we think happiness <em>consists</em>.</p>

<p>Instead of attempting to answer this question directly (which would require much more than one article), I will dispute the common belief that happiness only consists of mental states, or that to be happy means to be in a certain psychological state. This particular conception of happiness is widespread. Popular moral theories, including many (although not all) variants of Utilitarianism, rest on the idea that what humans desire are positive mental states, or pleasure. Furthermore, it seems to me that in our every day lives, our default intuition seems to support decisions that maximize the pleasure of ourselves or others. It requires deeper reflection to <em>override</em> this default concern for mental states for the sake of some other value. A common example of this is when somebody accepts that they have done something wrong — his initial instinct is not to admit his fault, for that would invoke feelings of shame and guilt. But upon further reflection, he realizes that the better action is to apologize and recognize his fault for whatever reason (so that he can avoid making the same mistake next time, or that he can become a better person, etc.).</p>

<p>In challenging this simple and compelling notion of happiness as purely a psychological state, the philosopher Robert Nozick employed a well-known thought experiment known as “The Experience Machine.” Imagine sometime in the future in which human beings have the technology and the understanding of neurophysiology to construct a machine that can perfectly produce any psychological state. Once plugged in, the individual’s thoughts and beliefs can be altered in any way — he can be made to think that he is the greatest writer in the world, the greatest musician, the most wealthy, the best looking, the most popular, the most well-liked, etc. He can be made to believe, and more importantly <em>feel as if</em>, his life is perfect in every aspect; his days would be filled with nothing but elation and contentment. Assume that, while in the Experience Machine, the individual believes everything he is experiencing is real, i.e., he is not aware of being in an experience machine, and further, has no memory of being plugged in.</p>

<p>Would you plug in? Nozick believed that most people would say no, especially when given enough time to think about it. This intuitive answer does not cohere with the view that happiness is constituted only by mental states. The Experience Machine can give us the best mental states imaginable, so why would we (or at least most of us) turn down the chance to plug in?</p>

<p>A common response in defense of mental state theories is that the thought experiment is too removed from our reality. The thought experiment is too abstract, or perhaps just too foreign, for us to consider and thus cannot yield any real insight into what we think of as happiness. But this thought experiment is not as far from reality as we think. Consider alcohol or recreational drugs. People consume these substances in order to make themselves feel a certain way. But because of the damaging side effects, many people do not think the experience worth it. Is it so hard to imagine a type of drug that exaggerates the effects of, for example, heroin, and does not have any negative side effects? If not, then it seems that at least a crude version of the experience machine is not so far from our reality, after all.</p>

<p>If this answer still isn’t satisfactory, consider the following alternative scenario, which is not only possible, but happens in some form or another quite regularly: Imagine someone who is happily married to a wife whom he loves more than anything. He genuinely believes that his wife loves him in the same way, but in reality, she doesn’t love him at all. In reality, she is cheating on him and can put on a perfect act to make her husband believe the contrary. Should we say that the husband is truly happy, in the sense of <em>flourishing</em>? Is that the kind of “happiness” you would want for yourself? Put another way, if we compare two men, both of whom believe that they are loved by their wives, but only one of who actually is, would we say that they are equally well off? Or does the one with a truly loving wife have greater claim to being <em>truly</em> “happy”?</p>

<p>Having established that the Experience Machine (or the alternative experiment) is valuable to use as a thought experiment, I return to the question of why our intuition tells us to reject the offer to plug in to the machine. The answer is simple: we believe that happiness is more than just a psychological state. We value something else beyond simply experiencing certain emotions and believing certain things — we value <em>actually accomplishing</em> the things we think we are accomplishing and <em>actually being</em> the person we think we are. Striving to do things and to become a certain person seems completely meaningless if it all takes place in our heads. We pity the beguiled husband even though he believes that he is in a perfect marriage, because in reality, the marriage is broken. However, this position does not commit us to saying that mental states play <em>no</em> role in happiness. Rather, the claim I wish to advance is that mental states do not play the <em>only</em> role in happiness.</p>

<p>The question remains: What else do we value in our happiness? What else <em>should</em> we value in happiness? The question seem closely connected to what we <em>value </em> in that, what we value gives us a framework for evaluating whether or not any given individual is truly happy, and further, for determining how to live our lives in pursuit of happiness. For instance, someone who values that his life be grounded in reality and not some imaginary virtual machine will not think consider life in the Experience Machine to be one of genuine happiness.</p>

<p>After hearing these arguments, some may still want to plug in. If I asked these individuals to compare the <em>same</em> life in the experience machine, and the same life outside of the experience machine, however, I suspect most of them would regard the life outside the machine as “better” in some way. In this paper I have not argued <em>why</em> life outside the experience machine is the better alternative, or, more generally, why happiness <em>should</em> <em>not</em> consist only of mental states. This would involve a discussion of what we value and find meaningful. In this article, I hope to have at least shown that for most of us, who <em>do</em> have the intuition to refuse the experience machine, mental states are clearly not enough. Perhaps actual success or the actual possession of goods like truth, love, beauty, dignity, and freedom are intrinsically valuable and thus play a role in happiness.</p>

<p><em>Originally published in Flourish, Yale’s Undergraduate Journal for the Interdisciplinary Study of Human Flourishing</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on Metaphilosophy: The Role of Philosophy in My Life]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/05/reflections-on-metaphilosophy-the-role-of-philosophy-in-my-life/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/05/reflections-on-metaphilosophy-the-role-of-philosophy-in-my-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I wish I could say that I had a sudden realization, some profound epiphany concerning the human condition. It would be more thrilling for the reader. Unfortunately, the insights that I have reached through philosophy usually come about through a much more gradual, much less dramatic process. In compelling me to alter my understanding and interpretation of the world, the process can be dauntingly uncertain and even painful. I consider this very process of critical thought “philosophy.” But before I continue, I must clarify the meaning of this word. By philosophy, I mean the process of thinking, perceiving, and judging oneself and the world rationally in accordance with empirical knowledge. Philosophy also refers to the study of general and fundamental problems concerning truth, ethics, and human existence. I will address both in this essay. Nowadays people tend to have a negative conception of philosophy. The word invokes images of grand ivory towers situated behind ivy walls. Inside the towers in an oak-paneled room a pretentious old man sits on a gilded armchair, living in luxurious decadence. Out of touch with real world issues and having never encountered adversity, he spends his time contemplating ideas to amuse his intellect. This is not philosophy. In my experience, even educated people frequently misconceive of philosophy as an esoterically useless discipline meant only for an intelligentsia out of touch with the world. Among university students for instance, philosophy is one of the most ridiculed majors, right next to art history and English literature. This attitude towards philosophy has always infuriated me, not only because it shows the underlying ignorance of the believer, but also because of its glaring irony. The course of my life thus far has led me to firmly believe that philosophy is the most practical and necessary of all human disciplines.</p>

<p>I did not always believe in philosophy. In fact, I did not even know what philosophy was until sometime during my sophomore year of high school. Rather than being introduced to it or stumbling upon it by chance, I was eventually led to philosophy by my intellectual curiosity. In every class, as soon as I questioned the material on a deep enough level, the same type of apparently unanswerable questions would keep recurring. Biology class defined life as a series of ongoing chemical reactions and suggested that consciousness is the mere exchange of sodium and potassium ions across gated protein channels in the brain. In questioning these definitions, I hit upon philosophical discussions of defining human life, the existence the Platonic soul, and the existence of free will. In English class, reading Hamlet compelled me to consider the ethics of suicide and the possibility of living a meaningful existence despite life’s inevitable tragedies. Even math class, during our study of the summation of infinite series, caused me to contemplate the idea of infinity and the limits of the human mind in conceptualizing the infinite. These are but a few examples in the myriad questions I struggled with during high school.</p>

<p>As I began to systematically contemplate each of these questions, I noticed how they converged and oftentimes complemented one another. The debate about the existence of a soul coincides directly with the god debate. The discussion about free will relates to the ethics of suicide. Thus, not only does philosophy underlie the various academic subjects, but it ties everything together. It acts as a sort of interdisciplinary network, allowing me to synthesize information from one area with that of another. This synthesis allows me to produce conclusions, useful facts which I use to make decisions. In real life, decisions rarely require only a single area of knowledge. All human decisions necessitate thinking about various issues that branch into science, humanities, and other areas of thought. So in a sense, philosophy better prepares me to make real life decisions by making sense of knowledge in the context of all other types of knowledge. It is self-evident that no knowledge has any useful application unless it is contextualized with knowledge from other areas.</p>

<p>I have just discussed the importance of philosophy in the academic realm, but philosophy also exists as a powerful way of thinking. The German philosopher Nietzsche states, “There are no facts, only interpretations.” Apart from the debate of the possibility of absolute truth, there exists the simple fact that interpretation is a necessary and integral part of human perception. One might ask, “What about the objective truths derived from math and science?” I am referring to perception with the intent of applying the information. Of course the fact “one plus one equals two” leaves no room for interpretation. But to make use of it one must interpret this fact in the context of a real life situation. For instance, does falling in love and marrying somebody mean that the two of you exist as a single entity? Or do you both exist separately? What degree of agency should each retain in such a relationship? These questions depend on the understanding that quantities change when combined, but the meaning of such a fact must still be interpreted. In other words, although there are definite facts about the physical nature of the world, these are not truths in the strictly human sense. Knowing one plus one equals two does not inform us on how we should think about ourselves and the world. Hard facts must be interpreted, or humanized, in such a way that allows them to be applied to our lives. It is through this very process of human interpretation that we construct our reality. Philosophy refines the way one interprets the information he receives. The philosophical approach to interpretation entails constantly thinking about external information and cross-referencing it with other facts, with the ultimate goal of reaching a useful and informed conclusion. By approaching the world with a severely critical eye that questions every iota of information it receives, one can reach the most objective conception of the given situation. This involves understanding the various internal biases of both the information giver and receiver. As discussed above, humans operate based on interpretation, not hard fact. No matter how hard they try to give an objective account, it is necessarily influenced by subjective interpretation. Furthermore, one’s own reception of information is unavoidably skewed by internal biases. People often bend things to hear what they want. Philosophy works to counter this two sided subjectivity, allowing one to reach the most objective reality. I had to steel myself with this mentality during the college search process.</p>

<p>Every year during the summer and fall, colleges unleash impressively aggravating advertising campaigns involving tons of paper, emails, and phone calls. In its wake lie acres of deforestation, overflowing spam folders, and millions of poor misled students. Colleges like to personally address the letters to students by first name, writing in a friendly tone hoping to draw them in. They use numbers to boast about the number of Nobel prizes their faculty have received, their annual endowment, and the racial diversity of the student body. They present their institution as alone possessing these characteristics, existing as the most perfect place in the world for you to spend the next four years. I can imagine how the unsuspecting high school junior can easily get lassoed by this type of advertising. In order to find a truly well-fitting college, I approached the process fully aware of the marketing strategies these institutions employed. Furthermore, I understood that the colleges I was applying to are essentially similar with regards to academic quality, diversity of student body, and social atmosphere, differing only in location and other minor characteristics. This approach, I would imagine, spared me the stress of desperately wanting to be accepted to the only college I thought would suit me. I realized that I was applying to a number of colleges I would be very happy at, and that in the end, the experience will depend more on how I use the institution’s resources rather than what resources it provided me. By attaining the most objective reality of the situation, I was able to create the most beneficial interpretation.</p>

<p>Part of interpreting a fact includes determining how valuable that fact is. As humans, we live our lives doing, or with the hope of doing, what we want. We only want what matters to us, what is meaningful and what is valuable. Philosophy aids me on this quest for existential meaning because what I care about is often not easily apparent. It requires a combination of life experiences and deep contemplation to realize what I truly care about. I’m not talking about simple pleasures which can be discovered through reflexive emotional responses. Watching an entertaining movie makes me happy, but the happiness is also shallow and temporary. Simple thrills do not motivate me in the long run. What makes life worth living is the promise of experiencing true, lasting meaning. For instance, it took me many years to fully appreciate my musical education. I always hated practicing and listening to jazz and classical music when I was younger. Now, listening and playing such music gives me a feeling of satisfaction that I don’t get from anything else. Although this may have been a result of my acclimation to music after studying it for so many years, I think the full explanation must acknowledge the fact that I tried to understand and relate to the meaning behind the music. After eight years of study, I know with certainty that I value jazz and classical music on the deepest level.</p>

<p>Having a philosophical state of mind means constantly questioning not only the accuracy of one’s perceptions but also the quality of one’s valuations. It is easy to convince yourself that you enjoy something you actually don’t. Although I have no experience with this, my older brother David shared his experience in the job market and the realizations he’s come to. He told me about how fresh college graduates are frequently misled by jobs with high salaries, not considering the value of the work itself. After graduating, my brother was offered jobs by banks and consulting firms with impressive salaries, but these were jobs that didn’t interest him. Instead he chose to explore the tech-startup industry, working for smaller groups with more modest salaries and lacking the financial benefits of large corporations. Because of this, he’s discovered a passion for computer programming and web development, something he never would’ve been exposed to had he decided to work for a bank. I’m sure that many adults find themselves in the doldrums of a job they hate, realizing after many miserable years that the salary does not outweigh the negatives of the work itself. This can be avoided if one always knows and prioritizes what he deeply values. Through this rationalization, one can easily conclude that money should be treated as a means, not as an end. Philosophy can help one realize that it is not money that is valuable, but rather the possibilities that money provides. By constantly reevaluating my values, I emerge with a more absolute and profound awareness of what is meaningful to me. Philosophy acts as an intellectual sieve, filtering out the refuse and ensuring that what remains is truly valuable to oneself.</p>

<p>I’ve offered my thoughts on the academic importance of philosophy as well as its personal importance in attaining the most objective conception of the world and in striving for true meaning. But the question still remains, what is philosophy? Defining it is difficult because it exists in so many different forms and contexts. In the broadest sense, I consider philosophy an intellectual process which uses reason to investigate and interpret the nature of oneself, one’s environment, and the relationship of the two. Furthermore, philosophy is an internal mode of thinking that is reliable under all external circumstances. In its most ideal form, philosophy should exist as a universal approach to human problems, from the mundane to the profound. Emphasis is placed on reason because only through systematic logic one can effectively determine consistency and inconsistency, and consequentially, right versus wrong and value versus lack of value. All of this philosophical thinking leads to the ultimate purpose of deciding how to live one’s life.</p>

<p>Only by first evaluating the world and oneself objectively can one then decide how to act, acting being the interface between the self and the environment. Only by first answering the question “What is?” can one answer “What should be?” Everyday life demands decisions from us of varying degrees, compelling us to ask ourselves what is moral and immoral. This dilemma presents itself to me every time I choose to illegally pirate music. On one hand, it’s against the law and could have very serious legal ramifications if caught. On the other hand, the artists of the music I pirate already passed away. Their estates would receive all of the commissions from purchases. Knowing them to be artists in the purest sense, I can comfortably conclude that they would rather want people to be exposed to their musical artistry and genius than for their estates to earn money. This is an example of how philosophy remains essential dealing with the question of “How should I act?” Philosophy rationally organizes one’s knowledge and principles to allow this question to be adequately addressed. Because I am constantly exposed to new situations and gaining new knowledge, my answers to this question constantly fluctuates. It is easy to stop considering new information, unintentionally reverting to an outdated ethical mode. As shown by history, the individual’s failure to update their opinions with new facts can lead to disastrous injustices. I remember feeling deeply disturbed when studying about events like the Holocaust, the Rape of Nanjing, and the My Lai Massacre. How could these things happen? How could human beings commit such terrible atrocities to one another, not only murdering and raping but also torturing and mutilating. What happened to the common sense and rational instinct that should have been screaming for an end? These are unanswered questions which will continue to haunt me. But part of the answer, I think, is the fact that the individuals relinquished their ability to independently reason and valuate. Hannah Arendt says, “The sad truth is that most evil is done by people who never make up their minds to be good or evil.” I agree with her idea of the “banality of evil,” that more often than not, human injustice is a result of a lack of thinking, and consequentially the lack of exercising good will. Evil does not arise from actively sinful perpetrators but rather from passively unthinking and prejudiced bystanders. The philosophical mindset both prevents the individual from succumbing to the prejudices of his own complacent intellect and that of others. The philosopher exists as an active agent promoting active thought and thus spreading active morality.</p>

<p>My life has led me to philosophy not out of choice, but out of necessity. My education and personal experiences demand that I answer questions which require a rigorous type of thinking satisfied only by philosophy. For me, the question that will always remain at the core of my life is “What makes life worth living?” More specifically, what makes my life worth living? All other philosophical questions lead to this one. Inquiries into the nature of the universe, one’s identity, and the proper ethics both depend on and help answer this singular question. It is one which is expressed in the art and literature of every era from every region of the world. Contemplation of this question remains at the core of the fundamental human experience. In this sense, there is a touching element of human tragedy to philosophy, that it paradoxically strives to answer a question that has no objectively definitive answer. There is something inexplicably beautiful and deeply inspiring about this Sisyphean struggle. As a philosopher, I’ve come to realize that one does not attain meaning by simply answering the question conclusively and putting the matter to rest. Rather, meaning is found in the very process of attempting to find an answer. What has made my life worth living are all of the things I’ve experienced during my philosophical quest, from the inspiring to the tragic, from the profound to the mundane, from the beautiful to the grotesque. What makes life worth living is the chance to be a philosopher – the opportunity to engage in this existential dialectic, to experience what it means to be human and to know what it means to be me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Response to Hume’s Argument Against the Existence of God]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/01/response-to-hume%e2%80%99s-argument-against-the-existence-of-god/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/01/response-to-hume%e2%80%99s-argument-against-the-existence-of-god</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><em>This is a response to an argument which Hume presents in his “Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion.”</em></p>

<p>Hume bases his dialectic on the idea that knowledge must rest on <em>a posteriori</em> experience rather than faith. This is because empirical evidence is essential to determining the plausibility of one idea over another in defining truth. Without experience ideas “…would all be possible; but, being all equally possible, he would never…give a satisfactory account for his preferring one of them to the rest” (182). Using this system he carefully refutes an <em>a posteriori</em> pro-God argument offered by Cleanthes. Cleanthes argues the existence of God by first asserting the similarity of the universe to a machine, something produced by man’s reason. Then, with the assumption that similar effects implies similar causes, Cleanthes claims that the universe must have been designed by an entity similar to a human being, possessing a similar faculty of thinking. This being is God. Philo dismantles this argument chiefly by attacking the validity of Cleanthes analogy. Philo claims, “Every alteration of circumstances occasions a doubt concerning the event” (183). Because there exists so many differences and unaccounted variables between man’s machines and the entire universe, Cleanthes analogy is unsound. Therefore, God cannot be claimed to exist in this manner. Philo then adds the argument that man’s faculty of reasoning exists as merely “one of the springs of the universe, as well as heat or cold, attraction or repulsion” (184). He equates the cause of thought to all other causes. Therefore, it is unreasonable to project the cause of thought as the ultimate cause of the universe. In his typical fashion, Hume uses skepticism to refute the God argument. Finally, assuming that such a grand analogy could be made, Hume subtly places “generation,” the system of birth observed in animals, as a more probable cause than reason. This is because humans have observed that reason derives from generation, but generation has not been observed to derive from reason. Therefore, generation exists as an earlier cause, thus it is more likely to be the ultimate cause.</p>

<p>Hume’s structured and logically rigorous manner of argument impresses me. The logical progression from one statement to the other appears quite sound. However, I question Hume’s assumption that <em>means</em> adapt to <em>ends</em>. In both Cleanthes and Philo’s arguments, there was a tacit acceptance of this idea without addressing the possibility that <em>ends </em>merely stem from <em>means</em>. What humans observe as the product of design may very well exist as the logical effect of the random arrangement of the universe. What we assume to be means may merely be the product of random chance. For instance, the arrangement of our solar system may have been due to chance rather than some intended cause. Perhaps Hume did not mean to imply this. Nevertheless, he implies a certain directed, or even conscious, <em>intent</em> in his idea of cause. I wish Hume addressed this assumption and clarified the nature of his idea of “cause.” I also question Hume’s seemingly casual relegation of human thinking as one of hundreds of causes. He describes it as “so minute, so weak, so bounded a principle” and “this little agitation of the brain which we call ‘thought’” (184). As a philosopher I believe Hume should hold higher regard for his single most important ability. It seems that he has extended his ideal of skepticism too far. Nevertheless, I consider his dismissal of thought as an interesting idea which could potentially inspire certain other ideas. For this reason, I will continue contemplating it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on the Nature and Importance of Reality]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2011/10/reflections-on-the-nature-and-importance-of-reality/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2011/10/reflections-on-the-nature-and-importance-of-reality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I wrote this partially in response to Lyle Zynda’s “The Nature of Reality and Why It Matters.”</p>

<p><em>Realism</em> is the idea that there exists an objective universe external to the human perception. Realist philosophers believe that the word “real” can refer to something independent of the human senses. What humans perceive may not necessarily constitute the definite, real world. According to one fundamental epistemological argument, humans do not experience reality directly. Rather, we merely perceive our brain’s interpretation of reality. This provides realists significant doubt that reality matches the subjective experience of humans. Furthermore, biologically the human body is only capable of receiving a limited range of sensory data. For instance, we cannot detect electromagnetic fields or perceive infrared radiation like other animals. Even though we don’t experience them directly, our science proves their existence. Therefore, it is possible that humans have a very limited grasp on the true reality.</p>

<p>This debate over the true nature of reality may seem like something whimsical and only for the amusement of dilettantes. Upon further reflection, how an individual decides to approach and answer this ultimately personal question holds enormous stake because it influences the way he conducts his life. Whereas the realist may decide to pursue a life of science in order to uncover what he believes to be an objective truth, a non-realist may decide to follow his instinct because reality is ultimately subjective. The question also deals with hope and imagination. Consider an individual who disagrees with the social norms of his time. If he was a realist, perhaps he would decide to live in contentedness because ultimately the world operates based on higher functions. The non-realist may be galvanized by his belief in the malleable nature of reality, that the status quo is not necessarily the way things have to exist.</p>

<p>Personally, I think this question matters in terms of choosing whether or not to believe in one’s current environment. I question Nozick’s claim that given proper thought, most people would not choose to enter an illusory state. Both Nozick and <em>The Matrix</em> strongly associate living in a dream with dishonor and corruption. I believe that because there is insufficient positive proof in the existence of an objective reality, humans are forced to trust their default, subjective experience. Accepting a subjective reality is not only more logical but preferable. Our senses render everything we experience and our consciousness processes and decides how we react. Humans are unable to step outside of our mind-body complex. Our whole lives are inescapably lived in a subjective manner, whether we believe in an objective reality or not.  Furthermore, what matters and what is meaningful exists as a human question. For all we know, the very concept of “meaning” is man-made. This definition necessitates subjectivity in the human quest for meaning. Therefore, logically I see no philosophical problem with choosing to enter a dream world that is more “perfect” (also a human, subjective concept) than the current world. Why would it matter to escape to a dream, if we weren’t ever aware of its artifice? How do we, as human beings, know for sure that we are not in a dream right now? This in conjunction with the assumption that human experience is subjective suggests the identical nature of the “real” world and the “dream world.” There exists no difference able to be grasped by the human.</p>

<p>In order for me to define what matters to me, I must first decide “What is reality?” For this reason, I will continue to ponder this question as I grow older.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Response to Carl Jung&#8217;s Concept of the Collective Unconscious]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2011/09/response-to-carl-jungs-concept-of-the-collective-unconscious/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2011/09/response-to-carl-jungs-concept-of-the-collective-unconscious</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>For my English class we had to read and respond to an <a href="http://www.carl-jung.net/collective_unconscious.html">interesting article</a>.</p>

<p>Coincidentally, this article formalizes a question I have been pondering for some time now. Is individuality merely an illusion for what is actually uniform throughout all humans? To what degree can humans vary in behavior and belief? Most importantly, do humans behave based on a system of innate formulas and biological patterns? This question holds immense stake because if our thoughts and actions <em>can</em> be defined as preconceived responses, then there is no such thing as free-will. If this is the case, we do not make decisions but rather carry out predetermined responses appropriate to the situation based on the stimuli we receive. But based on the reading, Jung does not extend his idea to such lengths as I have. He is unclear as to what extent the collective unconscious determines human behavior. Viewed like this, Jung’s idea becomes rather commonplace. It seems obvious that there would be similarities in parent-child relationships and the way humans respond to failure.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.google.com/url?source=imglanding&amp;ct=img&amp;q=http://www.metaphysics-for-life.com/images/humanmind.jpg&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=adRrTrDXDqje0QGZ3aHuBA&amp;ved=0CAYQ8wc&amp;usg=AFQjCNFU69xSgfka3KtnjOMQtIGoQb3dAg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Concerning the question I proposed at the beginning, I realize it may unfairly imply a one-sided answer. Human nature may be a combination of both Jung’s collective unconscious, which we have no control over, and individuality, which we do have control over to some extent. Then my question becomes, what is the relationship between the collective unconscious and free will? Is one dependent on the other? What has more influence over our lives?</p>

<p>Jung’s idea compels me to ask if the collective unconscious is stagnant or malleable. Does it exist as something eternal and unchanging? Or, as times progress and human society changes, does the collective unconscious change as well? Perhaps the collective unconscious remains fundamentally the same, but its manifestations change according to its environment. If this is the case, then the eastern tradition of discovering one’s Self will always remain pertinent.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
