<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-20T01:45:33-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://yoursite.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mental State Theory: An Inadequate Picture of Happiness]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2013/04/mental-state-theory-an-inadequate-picture-of-happiness/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2013/04/mental-state-theory-an-inadequate-picture-of-happiness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>In investigating questions of human happiness, it’s important to explore the very concept of happiness itself. Unfortunately, this word is used in myriad contexts and comes loaded with many meanings. For the purposes of this article, I will use the term to refer to the deeper type of happiness that we associate with human flourishing — the type of happiness we mean when we ask ourselves the question, “Am I <em>really</em> happy?”</p>

<p>Questioning this type of happiness itself will hopefully bring into focus a better picture of the nature of happiness and its role in human flourishing, as well as introduce important questions that must be addressed in giving an adequate account of happiness. Though I acknowledge the fact that happiness has an inescapably subjective nature — after all, each of us is made happy by different things — I think we can still hold meaningful discussions about the objective aspects of happiness, namely, what it is that we think happiness <em>consists</em>.</p>

<p>Instead of attempting to answer this question directly (which would require much more than one article), I will dispute the common belief that happiness only consists of mental states, or that to be happy means to be in a certain psychological state. This particular conception of happiness is widespread. Popular moral theories, including many (although not all) variants of Utilitarianism, rest on the idea that what humans desire are positive mental states, or pleasure. Furthermore, it seems to me that in our every day lives, our default intuition seems to support decisions that maximize the pleasure of ourselves or others. It requires deeper reflection to <em>override</em> this default concern for mental states for the sake of some other value. A common example of this is when somebody accepts that they have done something wrong — his initial instinct is not to admit his fault, for that would invoke feelings of shame and guilt. But upon further reflection, he realizes that the better action is to apologize and recognize his fault for whatever reason (so that he can avoid making the same mistake next time, or that he can become a better person, etc.).</p>

<p>In challenging this simple and compelling notion of happiness as purely a psychological state, the philosopher Robert Nozick employed a well-known thought experiment known as “The Experience Machine.” Imagine sometime in the future in which human beings have the technology and the understanding of neurophysiology to construct a machine that can perfectly produce any psychological state. Once plugged in, the individual’s thoughts and beliefs can be altered in any way — he can be made to think that he is the greatest writer in the world, the greatest musician, the most wealthy, the best looking, the most popular, the most well-liked, etc. He can be made to believe, and more importantly <em>feel as if</em>, his life is perfect in every aspect; his days would be filled with nothing but elation and contentment. Assume that, while in the Experience Machine, the individual believes everything he is experiencing is real, i.e., he is not aware of being in an experience machine, and further, has no memory of being plugged in.</p>

<p>Would you plug in? Nozick believed that most people would say no, especially when given enough time to think about it. This intuitive answer does not cohere with the view that happiness is constituted only by mental states. The Experience Machine can give us the best mental states imaginable, so why would we (or at least most of us) turn down the chance to plug in?</p>

<p>A common response in defense of mental state theories is that the thought experiment is too removed from our reality. The thought experiment is too abstract, or perhaps just too foreign, for us to consider and thus cannot yield any real insight into what we think of as happiness. But this thought experiment is not as far from reality as we think. Consider alcohol or recreational drugs. People consume these substances in order to make themselves feel a certain way. But because of the damaging side effects, many people do not think the experience worth it. Is it so hard to imagine a type of drug that exaggerates the effects of, for example, heroin, and does not have any negative side effects? If not, then it seems that at least a crude version of the experience machine is not so far from our reality, after all.</p>

<p>If this answer still isn’t satisfactory, consider the following alternative scenario, which is not only possible, but happens in some form or another quite regularly: Imagine someone who is happily married to a wife whom he loves more than anything. He genuinely believes that his wife loves him in the same way, but in reality, she doesn’t love him at all. In reality, she is cheating on him and can put on a perfect act to make her husband believe the contrary. Should we say that the husband is truly happy, in the sense of <em>flourishing</em>? Is that the kind of “happiness” you would want for yourself? Put another way, if we compare two men, both of whom believe that they are loved by their wives, but only one of who actually is, would we say that they are equally well off? Or does the one with a truly loving wife have greater claim to being <em>truly</em> “happy”?</p>

<p>Having established that the Experience Machine (or the alternative experiment) is valuable to use as a thought experiment, I return to the question of why our intuition tells us to reject the offer to plug in to the machine. The answer is simple: we believe that happiness is more than just a psychological state. We value something else beyond simply experiencing certain emotions and believing certain things — we value <em>actually accomplishing</em> the things we think we are accomplishing and <em>actually being</em> the person we think we are. Striving to do things and to become a certain person seems completely meaningless if it all takes place in our heads. We pity the beguiled husband even though he believes that he is in a perfect marriage, because in reality, the marriage is broken. However, this position does not commit us to saying that mental states play <em>no</em> role in happiness. Rather, the claim I wish to advance is that mental states do not play the <em>only</em> role in happiness.</p>

<p>The question remains: What else do we value in our happiness? What else <em>should</em> we value in happiness? The question seem closely connected to what we <em>value </em> in that, what we value gives us a framework for evaluating whether or not any given individual is truly happy, and further, for determining how to live our lives in pursuit of happiness. For instance, someone who values that his life be grounded in reality and not some imaginary virtual machine will not think consider life in the Experience Machine to be one of genuine happiness.</p>

<p>After hearing these arguments, some may still want to plug in. If I asked these individuals to compare the <em>same</em> life in the experience machine, and the same life outside of the experience machine, however, I suspect most of them would regard the life outside the machine as “better” in some way. In this paper I have not argued <em>why</em> life outside the experience machine is the better alternative, or, more generally, why happiness <em>should</em> <em>not</em> consist only of mental states. This would involve a discussion of what we value and find meaningful. In this article, I hope to have at least shown that for most of us, who <em>do</em> have the intuition to refuse the experience machine, mental states are clearly not enough. Perhaps actual success or the actual possession of goods like truth, love, beauty, dignity, and freedom are intrinsically valuable and thus play a role in happiness.</p>

<p><em>Originally published in Flourish, Yale’s Undergraduate Journal for the Interdisciplinary Study of Human Flourishing</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brad Mehldau&#8217;s &#8220;My Favorite Things&#8221;]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2013/02/brad-mehldaus-my-favorite-things/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2013/02/brad-mehldaus-my-favorite-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>Jazz musicians and educators always make comparisons between jazz improvisation and language. They talk of expanding one’s “jazz vocabulary” and “pacing” one’s solos effectively. They say that the best solos “tell a story.” In this way, the jazz soloist is analogous a rhetorician giving an improvised speech, attempting saying something meaningful to the audience. But sometimes, as is often the case with many of my favorite recordings, the artist seems engage in a soliloquy, full of introverted reflections. To name off the top of my head some musicians who do this a lot — Miles Davis, Wes Montgomery, and Bill Evans.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><img src="http://i.ytimg.com/vi/gClg7L_vqes/0.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>Brad Mehldau’s live recording of “My Favorite Things” is one such recording, and it’s one that means a lot to me both aesthetically and philosophically: the music itself simply sounds beautiful, and the emotions and thoughts it invokes in me are profound. Here is a <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X7fVnvJSRb4">link</a> to the piece.</p>

<p>In an <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/joseph-vella/brad-mehldau-the-art-of-s_b_823026.html">interview</a> with the Huffington Post, Mehldau said:</p>

<blockquote><p>“One fun surprise of this concert was “My Favorite Things.” It was not something I had played before – the Coltrane version is sacred to me. But I was going out for an encore and thought of it at the last moment, and it turned out to be for me anyways, one of the more compelling performances in the set – it had that story to it; it just kind of unfolded. Sometimes you find that and sometimes you don’t; sometimes you find it with no preparation or context at all and those moments are always great for me.”</p></blockquote>

<p>The piece seems even more impressive considering that it was spontaneous. But I guess you can hear that in the recording, how it progresses so naturally from a simple introduction to a compelling climax down to an ending. The recording really does sound like a soliloquy. We seem to be hearing the depths of Mehldau’s consciousness expressed musically. You know, those deep thoughts that exist but remain unknown to us until, in solitude, they gradually become lucid. This happens to me a lot during walks in quiet, peaceful places. For artists, I would imagine it happens during those rare instances of perfect artistic inspiration.</p>

<p>I listen to this piece a lot when I’m feeling melancholic, introverted, thoughtful, nostalgic, or any other feeling that would make me temporarily anti-social and weird. Anyhow, I thought I’d share this piece. Hopefully you hear something in it that you can relate to.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Music as Sound, Sound as Music]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/12/music-as-sound-sound-as-music/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/12/music-as-sound-sound-as-music</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>Leaning forward in my chair, I gripped my saxophone in anticipation. It was my first rehearsal with the Senior Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, the first musical group to ever intimidate me with its degree of talent and level of perfection. Widely regarded as one of the top wind ensembles in the world, the group is led by Michael Mucci — a conductor, educator, and mentor whom I admire deeply. During his opening remarks he said a curious thing.</p>

<p>“You are all here because you love sound.”</p>

<p>Strange, I thought. Why would he use the word sound? In my mind, the word “sound” stood uncomfortable close to “noise.” I wasn’t just producing mere sounds; I was making music — an art that requires skill and refinement, an art that is the opposite of noise. But for some reason, his words remained in the back of my mind and their meaning grew clearer as I matured musically through my high school years. Before this, however, I had to learn that listening to music is just as much a craft as making music.I didn’t always know how to listen to music well, and I still have a lot to learn. I remember how teachers would recommend that I listen to recordings like Miles Davis’ Kind of Blue and John Coltrane’s A Love Supreme, and how I would get bored after a few minutes. I thought it was because I didn’t understand the music theory underlying the jazz. But after devoting much time to learning about chord progressions and two-fives and secondary dominants, I still could not enjoy these records. Understanding that the tune “So What” has a modal structure that modulates up a half step in the bridge did not help me at all in appreciating the track.</p>

<p>Eventually, I was introduced to the concept of tone. Teachers emphasized the importance of developing a unique sound, asking me questions like “How would you describe your sound?” Dark, rounded, and pure, I would say. I knew that good tone was an important aspect of musicianship, but I hadn’t thought about it as something up to the musician to define. Miles Davis was always championed as having the quintessentially unique voice, so I began paying more attention to the way his trumpet sounded, not just the notes he played. With this attitude of listening for how things sounded holistically rather than how the notes were arranged, I gave Kind of Blue another shot. This time, I found myself able to sit through the full nine minutes of each track with a sustained interest. Instead of fixating on that particular bluesy lick that Cannonball played or the pentatonic scale that Coltrane used, I focused on how the richness of Bill Evan’s chords complemented Miles’ subdued tone. I noticed the contrast between the distinct sounds of Coltrane, Cannonball, and Miles, and how that lent the album a mosaic-like quality. I absorbed the recording’s general chilled, quiet, impressionistic ethos. I could go on about what I love about the album, but the point is that a simple shift in my listener’s attitude was all that I needed to understand the music. Studying jazz theory was unnecessary because listening to music involves something much more fundamental — it involves the skill of listening to sound.</p>

<p>I approached both new and familiar pieces of music with this new philosophy, asking the question: What kinds of sounds are these artists attempting to create? Sound, of course, gets conveyed in many different forms. In jazz, for example, the artist’s phrasing, tone, dynamics, intonation, rhythmic and melodic choices all characterize his sound. In classical, the composer’s orchestration and compositional choices as well as the performer’s interpretive choices comprise the sound. With this attitude, I listened with more focus; with more attention to subtle nuances and with more awareness of the piece as a whole. The result was that I appreciated a greater variety of music to a greater degree. Intrigued by new and unfamiliar sounds, I was less inclined to avoid music whose style wasn’t immediately familiar to me. That being said, I was not able to simply dive into the avant-garde. But I was able to immerse myself in the sound of a lesser-known, more unique composer such as Mahler or Tord Gustavsen.</p>

<p>And at its very core, music is just this — sound. After the last chord of every concert with the Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, my heart raced and my mind marveled at how magnificently the sound reverberated throughout the concert hall — entire seconds of sustained acoustic glory. The audience seemed to be equally mesmerized, remaining silent for a few seconds after the note had died out before applause broke out. A friend of mine went to one such concert and said to me afterwards, “The concert was amazing! Especially that last piece, there was just so much sound coming from all directions.” He had never studied music before and was able to enjoy a classical concert. Most people think jazz and classical music, or any type of non-pop music, are esoteric art forms, inaccessible to those who are untrained and inexperienced. But my near decade of intensive musical training and experience has only made me realize that this isn’t the case. Music is not about mastering the technicalities of a particular genre and being able to play specific notes in a specific style in a specific order. Music is about developing and expressing our natural, human instinct to produce different sounds and appreciate how they interact and combine in beautiful ways.</p>

<p>Later, my new understanding of music changed the way I hear everything around me, not just sounds in the concert hall or the practice room. Being a musician naturally made me more sensitive to any sound at all, and this came at a cost. For instance, when someone on my floor forgets to turn off their alarm and I’m in my room, struggling to write a paper, unable to ignore its constant blaring. Or when on a weekend morning the sound of a dozen high-powered leaf blowers, all humming at a slightly off-tune pitch, wakes me up from my lazy sleep. And try as I might, I simply cannot soundproof my room from the commotion that inevitably fills Old Campus every weekend night: drunken yelling, piercing screeches, blaring music, and senseless whoops. For someone who prefers quiet, being so hearing-sensitive makes Yale a very loud place indeed.</p>

<p>But then again, a heightened awareness of sounds can be refreshing. Now, sitting by an open window during summer nights, I am able to enjoy the concert of crickets — a cacophony during which polyrhythms emerge and evolve through a series of interlocking rhythms and pitches. And I love when the rich and dissonant call of a train echoes through the quietness of the weekday night, each time with a different blend of notes. My walk these days in the woods can be transformed into something memorable when a particularly lyrical bird sings a song. The ability to hear — to really hear — the sounds of the outside world adds a deeper dimension to my experiences. A memory of a trip to New York City would be incomplete without recalling the chaotic urban sounds of car honks, footsteps, and crowded murmuring. A climb to the summit of a mountain would be diminished without noticing the utterly imposing silence.</p>

<p>Learning to hear music as sound taught me how to hear sound as music. After all, music and sound are not separate realms, and neither are the concert hall and the city streets. It is all part of one single sonic environment that our ears inhabit. So the next time you are in the mood for music, try something new; maybe put on Kind of Blue. If you are feeling adventurous the next time you are out and about, try listening to the world as a recording studio full of new and experimental sounds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Look at Snow]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/12/how-to-look-at-snow/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/12/how-to-look-at-snow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><em>This piece is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lipogram">lipogram</a> in which I did not use the letter E (do a Ctrl-F if you don’t believe me). It was immensely challenging, but I had a fun time writing it. Enjoy.</em></p>

<p> 
Nothing can approach that first sighting of snow falling softly from a calm gray sky. Racing to my window and taking a good long look, visions of snowballs and toboggans and igloos flash through my mind. I am struck by a familiar youthful thrill. But I also think of walking through snowy woods. So I grab my stuff and go out.</p>

<p>Road lamps cast a glow, gold light diffusing warmly against a dark bluish background. Distant things sound faint. My boots crunch. Pausing, I pick up a soft but distinct sound, hard to put into words. Possibly how a thousand tiny crystal shards would sound colliding — a soothing, glassy tingling, akin to rhythmic rain. Withdrawn into isolation, I walk, not minding how cold it is. Soon, though, it turns into a raging blizzard of furious winds and blinding snow. I hurry back and as I rush in, I am struck by a familiar air: an aroma of smoky wood, a crackling of burning logs. Only during a snowstorm is this so inviting. A cup of hot cocoa awaits and I top it off with big marshmallows.</p>

<p>Sipping, I watch as snow’s sublimity transforms my world; all physical flaws vanish — no footprints, no sign of dirt; only a minimalistic fantasy. A blank canvas, full of possibility. And this, I think, is how all should look at snow.</p>

<p>But most don’t look at it this way. To many, snow is that awful stuff that sticks to scarfs and hats and hair, that stings skin, that drifts and blows around annoyingly; a cold dust that afflicts us in months around January. Moms and dads and various adults moan about how snow ruins roads, forming hazardous traps that all of us must unavoidably confront. Driving to work or school, typically quotidian, turns into an awful affair — traffic, plow trucks, and a slurry of salt, slush, and snow. Catching such words, I always think, <em>How sad, to think if that’s all snow is.</em> Having grown up in a Boston suburb, I’m fairly familiar with all things having to do with snow. Snow practically accounts for half of my childhood joy, a joy that I will not outgrow. So, naturally, I think that a man who knows only how to complain about snow is dogmatic and lacks a youthful outlook that savors snow for its fun and its bright and shining charm. Such a man is missing out on what’s important about snow — its magic. And that day that my school was caught amidst an abrupt snowstorm was nothing short of magical.</p>

<p>What a vivid sight — gothic archways, courtyards normally grassy, and old oaks showcasing a grand snowy cap. At midnight, vast crowds flock to Old Campus, lit by lamplight. Small groups form and soon, total chaos bursts out. A thousand kids frolic in snow on a Monday night, choosing fun and punting work. Snowballs fly this way and that. Occasionally, amidst raucous laughs and joyous shouts, a satisfying thud sounds; a good shot found its mark.</p>

<p>Panting, I go back to my dorm, worn out by our wintry fight. Collapsing on my chair, blood still pumping fast, I look out of my window, gazing out at snow dancing around a lamplight’s halo. I am calm again, happy, and I think: <em>Thank god for snow.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asking the Difficult Question]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/12/asking-the-difficult-question/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/12/asking-the-difficult-question</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>They bombarded us with warnings about the consequences of irresponsible drinking even before I got to college. The high school principal, teachers, and guidance counselors wanted us to understand that binge drinking is a serious matter — it leads to deaths. When I arrived at Yale, freshman counselors, college deans, and parents sternly reminded us of the same message. This time, they also talked about sexual health and the importance of verbal consent.</p>

<p>Of course, none of this surprised me. Clearly there is a growing awareness about the dangers associated with college-style drinking and hostile sexual climates. Last year, I read an article in Rolling Stone that was referred to me by my brother, friends, and websites like Reddit.com. It was about one student’s account of how Dartmouth’s frat culture dehumanizes their pledges. I googled around, wondering how credible the story was since it described things that seemed too gruesome to be true (stuff involving vomit and various other human wastes). One related article linked me to another and soon I found myself with a mess of tabs open in my browser, each with a story and an opinion about the shortcomings of college culture. The discussion was fierce, opinions were expressed through bold rhetoric and provocative claims. I discovered a scandal that occurred only two years ago at the college I was preparing to attend: pledges of the Yale fraternity Delta Kappa Epsilon, known as DKE, had chanted misogynistic slurs outside the Women’s Center. I spent that entire night going through a torrent of news reports, blog posts, and opinion editorials; some of them commented on campus culture, some of them denounced the Yale administration. Long threads of comments trailed each article, not just the casual musings of regular readers or the deliberately offensive statements of internet trolls, but substantial comments by people who cared about the issue. All of this sparked by one incident? Unlikely — this was definitely not just a passing concern, not just one of those controversies that inexplicably comes and goes. Behind this single Yale scandal was a fierce, ongoing debate about a serious problem in college culture.</p>

<p>I was amazed that nobody brought this up; not my freshman counselor, not my college dean, not the president of Yale. Not even in the context of talking about sexual safety did they mention anything about the DKE scandal that occurred only two years ago. Instead, to justify their grave warnings, they said, “it’s for your safety.” Drinking is bad because it has immediate dangers associated with it: it can lead to inappropriate sexual activity, it can leave someone physically vulnerable in a dangerous situation, drinking too much poisons the body. Lack of sexual consent is bad because someone’s emotional and physical safety is violated when he or she is pressured into unwanted sexual activity. Not to mention, both are illegal.</p>

<p>Yes, safety is an important consideration, but is that all that is important? While I acknowledge that this is a legitimate concern, I am not just interested in what is safe; I am interested in what is moral — in what is right. Why, during orientation, did nobody approached the issues of drinking and sex from the ethical lens I had encountered in the online articles? I can understand why counselors and deans would refrain from offering these views; the matter gets to be intimately personal, inevitably leading to discussions of individual values and such. But why did these mentor figures, meant to guide us through our first days of college, pretend that drinking and sex is only an issue when physical and emotional safety is concerned? From what I read in the articles and comments, the scandal didn’t stir up the greater community so aggressively because someone might have gotten emotionally or physically hurt; the event was so controversial because a group of Yale students came together and collectively did something so obviously immoral. Not one of the participants paused to think about what they were saying, why they were saying it, and whom they were saying it to. This is what disturbs me the most — that it was a real example of the herd mentality authors like Orwell, Huxley, and Bradbury warned us about.</p>

<p>The morality of college-style drinking and sex needs to be discussed in a more open and purposeful manner. Many of the authors of the blogs and articles I read were students of Yale College with distinctive voices, whose contributions fueled the discussion. So why should it be any different in the common room, the dining hall, or the courtyard? Oftentimes in casual conversations, students will shy away from critically examining college students’ attitudes towards drinking and sex, mirroring the way Yale mentors avoided the question. They avoid questions like, Why are binge-drinking and the one night stand glorified? Should they be glorified? I take it that in general, people are afraid to critique the accepted ethical norms for fear of making moral judgments on individuals. But mute acceptance of the popular attitudes is itself a moral judgment because without criticism, the social atmosphere can begin to impose the very moral pressures people try to prevent. Furthermore, our ethical choices affect our personal lives in significant ways that extend beyond just the realm of safety. Ethical choices can also profoundly affect our happiness and our personal growth. Given the stakes, I don’t think ubiquity is a reason to assume that the given standards are right and more importantly, it is not a reason to assume that the standards are universally accepted and that conversation is unnecessary. Clearly not everybody agrees with the stereotypical college party mentality. Individuals are the ones disagreeing and starting the conversation in the first place.</p>

<p>The larger and more essential question is this: what do I as an individual think about the morality of the behavior around me? The DKE incident happened because individuals each made a decision to participate, whether consciously or unconsciously. A community’s ethical norms rest on individual values and decisions, so in questioning the ethics, it would make sense to also question personal values, those both of oneself and of others. The platitude, “Don’t judge,” warns us to avoid attacking others’ personal values and it is often the response I get when I start challenging the glorification of binge-drinking and the “hook up” culture. The phrase is an easy out for those who confuse honest discussion with dogmatic assertion, for those who fear confronting the difficult yet important topics that loom close to personal values. People can’t stand to face questions like, “Why do some college students choose to get drunk and suffer a hangover repeatedly?” “Why are one-night stands in which the two partners never speak to each other again considered worthwhile?” When I or others pose these questions, we are not declaring our moral superiority. Rather, we are looking for honest discussion about a subject that matters to us. Of course we all hold different beliefs as to what is right and wrong, and sometimes one person’s values can directly oppose another’s in a very antagonizing and uncomfortable way. But that’s okay — the point is not to simply agree with others or reach the same conclusions. The point is to agree to have this crucial conversation, to ask the questions that matter but too often have been passed over in silence.</p>

<p>I don’t believe that wild and shameless partying is anything glorious. In fact, I have more than a few moral qualms about it and because of this, I ask questions like these: in parties, why is alcohol nicknamed the “social lubricant,” and treated as a replacement for honest conversation? Why do some people admit to using alcohol as a way to tolerate “how bad the parties are?” If the parties are that bad, why go at all? It seems that students feel obliged not only to avoid evaluating the culture, but also to participate in it. I wonder how happy they are, and I suspect that not all of them feel comfortable if some need alcohol for such reasons, in such high quantities. One Yale guest columnist writes, “Trust me: freshman year means no shame. To the contrary—you will cherish your poor choices. You will delight to see that hook-up—whom you will not acknowledge—eating in your dining hall.” From the freshmen I’ve met so far, I don’t think most of us intend to treat our first year at Yale as a chance to recklessly indulge ourselves, to “cherish” mistakes because “freshman year means no shame.” So why aren’t more students advocating alternatives to this reckless, shameless attitude? My friend offered this explanation: people engage in the popular college culture because it feels liberating to do something traditionally considered taboo. But then again, I’m not satisfied with this answer. I think there’s something else motivating this unrestrained, unashamed behavior. Personally, I suspect that it has something to do with a lack of careful thought about one’s choices. I don’t think most college students are rational hedonists who consume dangerous amounts of liquor and wake up in strangers’ beds after thinking it through with reason, concluding that this was in their best interest.</p>

<p>One way to rephrase the difficult question is: What do I really want? Fondly called the “bright college years,” we are told by older folk that college is a time to find ourselves, to discover more about our own identities. It is also a time to continue creating ourselves. I intend to do just that by forming my own opinions and voicing them with an ear to what others have to say. I will either agree or disagree with the views of popular culture, but always with my own reasons, always with an evaluative focus. But most importantly, I hope to inform and possibly amend my personal moral values by the wide variety of perspectives I will encounter in honest discussions and hopefully, in honest behavior.</p>

<p>And I will always be asking myself, What do I think is right?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Little Things]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/11/the-little-things/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/11/the-little-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>            About to board the plane, I checked my bag for my laptop and passport. Caitlin checked for her stuffed animal—an odd-looking, brown creature called “Domo”—neglecting, among other valuables, an Apple laptop, expensive souvenirs from China, and her family heirloom ring. Teasingly I shook my head and asked, “What would you do if the Domo wasn’t there?” She looked me in the eyes with an expression of terror, deliberately dramatic but also, I think, partly sincere. “I would start bawling like a baby.” she replied. To anyone who doesn’t know her, it would seem odd that she, a college student, considers a child’s toy her most valuable possession. It would seem even more odd that she falls asleep every night clutching Domo to her chest. “He’s cozy and reminds me of home,” she would say so matter-of-factly, as if no further justification were needed.</p>

<p>This isn’t her only childlike idiosyncrasy.</p>

<p>In high school we would often go on walks after school and on the weekends, strolling through the center of town and the local parks. Anytime she caught sight of a dog, she would point and exclaim, “Doggie!” Whenever we passed an ice-cream shop, she would improvise some excuse and moments later I would find us sharing an ice cream cone stacked to the brim.</p>

<p>She was a mystery I couldn’t quite figure out. I knew she behaved this way partly to amuse me and partly because she liked being silly. But there was something else to her youthfully capricious behavior, an element of sincerity that couldn’t be feigned. I found myself wondering if part of her defied growing up and chose instead to remain as a child, unabashed and uninhibited.</p>

<p>She certainly possesses the honesty and spontaneity of someone much younger. Consider me for contrast: I am an incessant planner driven by purpose, someone who feels compelled to organize even the leisure activities of a lazy Sunday afternoon: go to the library from one to two, walk around the Town Hall from two to three, go home and read from three to five. Caitlin, on the other hand, prefers to go where whim and circumstance take her. She would take me on walks without a destination, content to aimlessly wander the suburban roads and woodsy trails. As we treaded into the unfamiliar, I would grow uncomfortable, wanting to stop and figure out where we were. Looking over at her, I would see only a pair of curious, light-brown eyes. “I love wandering and seeing where I end up,” she would say. One time the path took us to a tall deserted bridge that passed over a wide marsh. It was rusted and covered in what looked like years of graffiti—thick lines of color overlapping to create a fluorescent chaos. Another time the path took us to a miniature peninsula that jutted out into a lake. There we found a forgotten bench, where we spent an afternoon talking and daydreaming the hours away. <em>So this is what can happen without a plan,</em> I thought<em>. So this is what it means to adventure</em>.</p>

<p>With Caitlin, rain was no longer an inconvenience; it was an invitation to go outside and see the world in gray and silver. Getting lost was no longer an accident; it was a chance to discover something new, to stumble upon a delightful surprise.</p>

<p>It still surprises me that we ended up together despite our opposing personalities—I always wanting to determine something’s deeper meaning, she able to appreciate it for what it simply <em>is</em>. And this quality, though I associate it with her youthful side, gives her unique insight in understanding her friends and family. Sometimes her mother would come home from a long day of work, mentally exhausted and emotionally frustrated. With a pained sigh and an attempt to seem happy, her mother would say, “Hi dear, how was school?” Sensing that her mom was silently being overwhelmed by a torrent of stressful thoughts about how terrible the day was, Caitlin would sit her down and bring her a cup of hot tea. “Let’s watch a crappy movie tonight. I’ll run to CVS and pick up some popcorn and gummy worms,” she would say. She knew her mother too well.</p>

<p>Caitlin makes it easy to appreciate those small things that inevitably escape one’s notice on any given day, dwarfed by bigger, more pressing matters. She inspires joy even in the most difficult circumstances. When I left for college, she gave me a jar filled with hundreds of colorful paper slips, each with a little note. She wrote, “Here’s a jar of random thoughts. Pull one out to make you smile when you miss me.” I remember a few long nights when I could do nothing but lie in my bed and feel the weight of her absence. I would pull out some paper slips from her jar, not expecting anything to bring me out of my misery, especially not words on pieces of paper. But of course, she knew exactly what to say.</p>

<p>“Take a break from the textbooks and go for a walk.”</p>

<p>“Don’t forget to add to our bucket list, we need awesome ideas.”</p>

<p>“When you’re feeling down, play some Frank Sinatra to remind yourself that you’re classy.”</p>

<p>Sometime later, Caitlin mailed me a copy of <em>The Little Prince</em>. Sitting in a quiet courtyard one afternoon, I put aside the Nietzsche tome (what I was reading for leisure at the time) and read this children’s book instead. The story about a prince from a tiny planet and his journey through the stars refreshed me, more than Nietzsche would have. I especially enjoyed the cartoonish watercolor illustrations.</p>

<p>A handkerchief hangs by her bedside that reads, “Life is short. Enjoy the little things.” But despite her eye for the little things, she is also vulnerable to big things. The day Caitlin received news that her Aunt’s cancer was getting worse, a glossy, unfocused look replaced her charming smile; blankness took the place of the subtle yet charismatic smile that always lingered on the corners of her mouth and the tops of her cheeks. She grew quiet, preferring neither to speak nor to listen. She passed by dogs and ice cream stores without expression, and when I pointed them out trying to cheer her up, she would only smile weakly. “What do you want to do today?” I asked. “I don’t know, I’m fine with anything,” she replied automatically. After several such instances, I realized that just as her mood can be lifted by the world, it can also be dragged down. Since the world doesn’t always present itself in an uplifting light, her spontaneous personality comes at a cost. And even when happy moments occur, they are, after all, only “little things.” A stuffed animal cannot possibly comfort her for the fact that her aunt has cancer.</p>

<p>Even when Caitlin retreats from the world into an inner melancholia, I want to believe that her lively side hasn’t disappeared, but that it has only been overshadowed. The problem is, nobody—not her family, not her friends, not I—can bring her out of those moods the way she can for others. None of us seem to have Caitlin’s youthful spirit that lets us see and express how comforting a stuffed animal, how delicious an ice cream cone, or how utterly exciting a dog can be. So we end up feeling helpless, able to sympathize with her but unable to console her.</p>

<p>Recently Caitlin had been buried by an enormous workload (typical for students of MIT), and was having trouble sleeping. Try as I might, my words had not been able to reassure her that things would turn out okay. But this afternoon, she sounded different when I called. I could once again hear signs of the characteristic energy; she spoke faster, with a certain lilt. Every so often she laughed. Caitlin described her first tutoring session that afternoon. “Since it was the first day, we went to a playground and played together so my kid could get to know me. She’s seven years old and so cute!” She talked about all the adorable things her kid did and said and how happy it made her. She sounded like herself. Perhaps no one can animate her spirit like a child can. Perhaps, just as Caitlin reminds us what it’s like to be young at heart, children remind her of the same. “My kid was so honest and enthusiastic, so much more than adults.”</p>

<p>As I’m writing this, trying to sort out all my memories and thoughts in an attempt to produce a cohesive and complete depiction of her, one memory keeps recurring. It’s February. Snow covers the ground—the kind that forms a week after a snowstorm, shining brightly under the sun and crunching underneath boots. We’re on vacation with a couple of friends, planning to spend four nights at a quaint rental home in Vermont’s countryside. Rolling hills, small dirt roads, and colonial houses dot the landscape. Besides the occasional smoke rising from a chimney and the infrequent passing of a car, things are still and quiet. Things could not be more idyllic. One night we build a fire in the backyard. Nestled beneath many layers of clothing, we sit close to the burning logs. After a short while our friends go inside, preferring the couch and TV. Caitlin and I stay outside, enjoying the fire’s dancing light, inviting warmth, and rustic smell. We sit there without speaking, content to gaze into the flames and listen to the crackling. I look over at her, about to ask if she wants to head in, but I stop. She looks mesmerized by the fire, her eyes holding that distinct brightness, but more intense, and accentuated by the reflection of the flames. She snuggles against me and tears roll down her cheeks.</p>

<p>“This is so perfect,” she says.</p>

<p>I feel a twinge of discomfort because I know she will lose this feeling once we go back home.</p>

<p>This same feeling translates into worry as I think about Caitlin in the context of college. During her time at MIT, she, like all college students, will have to face unavoidable questions about her future — an abstraction that becomes real in the form of majors and internships and financial independence. The same emotional sensitivity that allows her to delight in the little things makes her especially vulnerable to the practical matters that feel much more significant. She will certainly have to give up much of the time she would have spent getting lost on long walks and rejoicing in rainy days. But, being in an environment meant to transform students into full-fledged adults, will she have to give up her youthful spirit? I worry about whether or not this part of her is being diminished. I worry about how happy she is. I worry about how hard it is for Caitlin to be herself.</p>

<p>But then she sends me a handwritten letter of elegantly rounded letters occasionally punctuated by endearing smiley faces, and I am reminded that she is still the same Caitlin. Then she visits me and I see the same pair of light-brown eyes and the same rosy cheeks raised in anticipation of a smile. And somehow, in that moment, I am convinced that college cannot take this away from her, this defiantly youthful spirit that is essential to her very nature. I can imagine seeing her in four years, more mature and independent by anyone’s standards, but still the same girl at heart.</p>

<p>“This is so perfect,” she would say again, as someone able to see the world through the eyes of youth; someone for whom the delight of Domo and dogs and winter fires is simply too valuable to give up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Search For Peace – Mccoy Tyner]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/11/search-for-peace-mccoy-tyner/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/11/search-for-peace-mccoy-tyner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><img src="http://www.lobosenbolos.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/mccoytyner.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I’ve always had this album in my collection because it’s one of those “classic” Blue Note albums, but I never gotten around to listening to it, except maybe once or twice when I had to study the tune “Contemplation.” One track on this record stands out to me — “Search For Peace” — and I’ve been listening to it non-stop. Besides the flawless playing of four jazz legends, I love the song as a composition. I rarely encounter pieces that sound more structurally complex than their actual form, in this case a standard AABA. I like the modal-esque bridge and the three ii/V’s modulating down half a step in the last four bars of the A section.</p>

<p>The track echoes the spiritual ethos that defined much of Coltrane’s music. That’s no surprise, given that Tyner played with Coltrane and recorded with him on many landmark recordings (The Love Supreme, for instance). However, the recording has much more space and subtlety than Coltrane’s music. Compare “Search for Peace” with Coltrane’s “Central Park West” and you will know what I mean.</p>

<p>But music jargon aside, it’s a great recording — one of those pieces that both jazz connoisseurs and casual listeners can appreciate. I’d even venture to say that it’s a timeless recording, like any of the tracks on Kind of Blue, that offers something different upon each new listen.</p>

<p>Do yourself a favor and <a href="http://open.spotify.com/track/4qRJ7ZJyfzchEd2fjle7Bz">listen to the song.</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Semester and Autumn]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/11/first-semester-and-autumn/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/11/first-semester-and-autumn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>These are some of the pictures I’ve taken with my iPhone 5 recently. Most of them are filtered with Instagram (which really is a great app when it’s not just used to “mupload” the sushi you had last night).</p>

<p>A story lies behind each of the pictures.</p>

<p>Yale is a great place for adventuring.</p>

<p>[![Journal][2]][2]</p>

<p>[![Harkness][3]][3]</p>

<p>[![Harkness After a Sunshower][4]][4]</p>

<p>[![Law School Archway][5]][5]</p>

<p>[![Law School Corridor][6]][6]</p>

<p>[![Law School Courtyard][7]][7]</p>

<p>[![Copper Sulfate][8]][8]</p>

<p>[![View from Science Hill][9]][9]</p>

<p>[![Compass at the top of East Rock.][10]][10]</p>

<p>[![Silliman Roof][11]][11]</p>

<p>[![Squirrel in LDub][12]][12]</p>

<p>[![Boston][13]][13]</p>

<p>[![Wellesley][14]][14]</p>

<p>[![Autumn looks best at home.][15]][15]</p>

<p>[![Beinecke in the Sun][16]][16]</p>

<p>[![Berkeley South in a Blizzard][17]][17]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Without Words]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/10/without-words/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/10/without-words</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><em>The following is meant to be an addendum to my previously posted essay, “The Woods and I, and Her.” A lipogram is a form of writing in which a certain letter or group of letters is suppressed. In this case, I suppressed the letter E. Writing it was enjoyable—for the first ten hours or so.</em></p>

<p>I was amidst autumn’s full glory. During a gradual transition in my town’s visual backdrop, that distinctly rich viridian color of spring was transforming into a brilliant gold. Fall, an annual occasion promising natural and satisfying tranquility, spurs my mind to think in privacy. But this fall I was always with Caitlin, walking on trails winding through woods and parks. Writing this stirs up nostalgia, for I miss my town’s distinct, idyllic charm. No, that’s not it. I miss that girl who I can talk to without words. I miss sitting on that wood platform with Caitlin, hand in hand, taking in a calmly flowing brook’s bubbling sounds. In Caitlin’s company, words can act as linguistic masks, trivial sounds, falling unsatisfyingly far from truth. In such situations, which almost always occur following instants of surprising bliss, words simply fail. For all I know, I could just lack a good vocabulary. But also, such thoughts thwart a logical, syntactical organization. Anyways, Caitlin and I could pass long durations without talking, that which I could not possibly do individually. Again and again I saw how wrong I was about joys of privacy and isolation. Without Caitlin, autumn would lack that particular quality so captivating that I can savor it still, as I am writing. I could say similar things about any month, any day, any hour that I was with my girl.</p>

<p>My journal, which usually lay in dust, ran into gradually rising amounts of ink—a runoff of thoughts that my mind could not contain. I saw its transformation into a bank of autobiographical narrations and individual ruminations. Flipping through my journal, I know that words, again, fail; all words that is, but this singular “Caitlin.”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Woods and I, and Her]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/09/the-woods-and-i-and-her/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/09/the-woods-and-i-and-her</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><em>“Impossible, I realize, to enter another’s solitude. If it is true that we can ever come to know another human being, even to a small degree, it is only to the extent that he is willing to make himself known.”</em></p>

<p><em>— Paul Auster</em></p>

<p>Growing up, I often pondered about happiness and the value of life, which for me still remains intimately connected to aesthetic pleasure. These questions were always on my mind as an intellectual obsession of sorts. To avoid a long and arduous story about my philosophical wanderings, I’ll simply say this: I concluded that the experience of happiness is a profoundly personal one that cannot be adequately communicated between individuals. That is not to say I thought happiness was only possible while alone, but rather that I thought happiness was most <em>meaningful</em>when experienced by oneself. By meaningful happiness, I mean the kind of feeling you get when, during a perfect autumn day, you walk through a forest of brilliant yellows and oranges and reds, wondering if these truly are earthly colors. I mean the feeling you get from reading a line of verse that resonates so deeply with meaning and sound that you are forced to stop and repeat the line over and over. I mean happiness of the deepest, most profound sort. This meaningful happiness that I speak of is elusive and hard to describe in a single word, but once experienced it cannot be mistaken for any other kind of happiness.All of these thoughts were, of course, built around my predisposition towards an almost solipsistic independence, which itself correlated with my apparent inability to feel satisfied with what apparently gave others happiness. My theory endured until one summer night.It was the end of my junior year in high school, a year fraught with academic anxiety about standardized tests, looming college applications, and grade maintenance. I had been invited to a backyard bonfire party where friends would spend the night celebrating the arrival of summer. I didn’t plan on going, preferring instead to spend the night alone, perhaps taking a walk through the woods, maybe staying home and playing my sax; I needed time alone to clear my head of all the anxiety-producing clutter that had accumulated over the year.</p>

<p>The day before the party, a classmate asked if I was going. We had studied together occasionally but certainly weren’t close enough to be considered friends. I gave her my usual response: “I can’t make it, I’m doing something else that night.” To my surprise she asked me what I was doing instead. Caught off guard by her sincerity, I responded honestly, “I plan to go for a walk or something, you know, something quiet. I’m not in the mood for a party.” And even more to my surprise, she asked if she could join me. “I’m not a party person either,” she said.</p>

<p>Caitlin suggested that we walk around Lake Waban at Wellesley College. Tucked into the edge of campus, the lake had evaded me despite my extensive knowledge of the town trails. I found myself in a situation where I was a follower, relying on Caitlin to lead the path. “I come here often,” she said, “it’s especially pretty right before the sun sets.” I could not escape a feeling of skepticism which conditioned my expectations and provoked certain questions. <em>Why does she want to walk with me? How could she understand what I consider beautiful?</em> Nature walks were for me very personal, a time to reflect and contemplate in isolation, away from the distracting noise of cars and people, a time to witness nature’s beauty. But of course, I never mentioned any of this to her. I didn’t want her to think I had something against her, or to misinterpret me further and think I had something against people in general. I was caught in an uneasy position, too worried about offending her and too uncertain to express my honest self.</p>

<p>And so we met on an early summer evening, each of us about to embark on a walk with a near stranger. The air felt cozy, somewhere in between the heavy humidity of late summer and the sharp dryness of autumn. The moderate temperature and slight chill of the breeze vivified my senses. It was about an hour to sunset. I heard nothing except the crickets and their evening songs. She was waiting for me, sitting on a bench looking out at the lake. I noticed how comfortable she looked, hands folded neatly in her lap and eyes focused on some distant point. She was wearing a white sundress embellished with red flowers, matched with a brown braided belt and flip flops.</p>

<p>She looked lovely.</p>

<p>“Ready?” she asked.</p>

<p>The initial awkwardness I usually felt with a stranger dissolved as soon as we started talking. Walking through a marshy patch across a flat wooden bridge, she said, “See that pond over there? It’s called Painter’s Pond because a paint company used to dump waste into it. But I’m glad that’s over. This place is too beautiful.” Then the trail wound through dense woods of maples and oaks, the remains of broken stone foundations, and the homes of squirrels and deer. The more we talked, the more I appreciated her company. “I used to live in Southborough when I was little. Our backyard faced the woods and I had this favorite rock I would climb. It was so nice there. Part of me still misses those woods.” We talked about school, summer plans, friends, and other minor things, but the conversation kept coming back to our immediate surroundings: the leaves, the water, the sky. It occurred to me that I didn’t find her presence distracting at all. In fact, I felt completely at home with myself, with her, and the woods. Gradually we talked less and less, too immersed in the quiet sounds of nature as day gives way to night. At this point I was aware of the undeniable reality that we were sharing this moment together, and not just on some superficial level.</p>

<p>It felt liberating, but I didn’t immediately understand why. Further reflection after the fact compelled me to see my previous preference for solitude in a very different light. My old attitude involved only the awareness of myself, an awareness I now realize to be relatively single-dimensional that did not need me to hear or acknowledge another pair of footsteps alongside mine. This was precisely what I felt for the first time as she walked beside me – the intimacy of solitude without its burden of loneliness.</p>

<p>At the end of the trail an elegantly stonewalled terrace overlooked the entire lake. Together we sat down on top of the wall, legs dangling above the water. “Isn’t this amazing?” she said, gazing up at the warm colors casted by the setting sun, a dazzling array of pinks, reds, purples, and blues. No other words were spoken. For the first time it felt as though someone else was witnessing beauty in a way that resonated with me. Her presence was something tangible that made the world around me appear more vivid. Ironically, she was the very “distraction” that I had always dreaded because I couldn’t help but marvel at her more than the sunset, but, contrary to the suspicions of my old attitude, she did not dilute the aesthetic experience. She unabashedly returned my glances, her dark brown hair and eyes reflecting the rich colors of the sky.</p>

<p>But I do not intend for this to be a story about love or what I consider to be true love. Nor do I intend that this be a story about how I met the most beautiful girl in the world. This is a story about how a romantic connection brought me to realize that profound feelings are enhanced when mutually appreciated.</p>

<p>The whole evening had been building up to this moment, a realization of such clarity that it left no room for skepticism. The feeling was more than just intellectual though. As I sat there looking out over a most perfect landscape, I felt invigorated with a feeling of deep aesthetic appreciation. Here I learned that the meaning of beauty gains a new dimension when mutually understood and freed from the limiting window of subjectivity. The moment felt sacred. Thus my lifelong assumptions about the truest happiness being exclusively personal fell apart. We spent the rest of summer together making memories gazing at the stars, eating ice cream, swimming in the ocean, activities that would’ve been mundane and easily forgotten had I done them alone. Months later, we sometimes walked the same path around the lake, recalling that night like it was yesterday.</p>

<p>Nowadays, being away from her at college, I look for other people to share moments of beauty with – something proving to be incredibly difficult, again because I am constantly looking for something else, something beyond ordinary expectations. Perhaps I am falling into the confines of an attitude similar to the one I overcame as I increasingly find myself wishing that I could share it with her and part of me wanting to share it <em>only</em>with her. But then again, perhaps her ability to relate to me is singular. Perhaps this, this irreplaceability of one’s company, is what love is. She is, after all, the girl who showed me that happiness is most meaningful when shared.</p>

<p>[![][2]][2]</p>

<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Concerning McCullough&#8217;s Speech]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/06/concerning-mcculloughs-speech/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/06/concerning-mcculloughs-speech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>During this past week following Wellesley High School’s Graduation, various commentaries regarding Mr. McCullough’s speech have been posted all over the internet. It even hit the front page of <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/videos/comments/urz30/youre_not_special_graduation_speech_honest_and/">Reddit</a>. In this day and age, 1700 upvotes and counting on Reddit means that the post might as well be on the front page of the newspaper. But it annoys me that much of the commentary is negative. Although most of these negative reviews seem to surface from the lower echelons of the internet (e.g., “Boston.barstool.sports.com” where one poster said, “But if you don’t think this dude is one more school year away from going postal and shooting up this school, you are outside of your mind”), I think it’s a shame that even a speech presented in such an accessible form through carefully chosen, non-academic words could send contrary messages. It’s clear that McCullough wrote this speech to an audience of all sorts, not only the young intellectual graduates and the parents of a wealthy suburb. He wrote this speech to convey an important and universal message for everybody struggling to find that elusive balance between what one <em>needs</em> to do and what one <em>wants</em> to do in life.</p>

<p>It is the tension that springs from this very conflict that causes so much controversy around his speech. One commenter on Reddit stated, “It’s a good attitude to carry if you want some stability in your career and maybe rise to some middle management position, but not such a reasonable mindset if you have any real ambition in life…at it’s core it’s a cynical exhortation for the graduates to keep their heads down and just do what they’re told.” Some of you might chuckle at the irony; this is the exact <em>opposite</em> of what McCullough intended to convey. The commenter’s mistake lies in his conception of “ambition.” Immediately he establishes “stability in your career” and job position as the stakes of the argument. Moreover he suggests a connection between the position of one’s job and his degree of independence. This statement represents what I think is an increasingly problematic and outdated perspective on success and the proper way to live one’s life.</p>

<p>Having recently gone through the college application process, I’ve had to think about my major, graduate school, my future career, etc. Parallel to these, I’ve had to think about the value of brand name schools, the importance of salaries, and practical majors versus impractical. In other words, I’ve had to think about the meaning and importance of prestige – markers of reputation that can distinguish you on a paper resume. For truly, what other connotations can that word imply? In a nutshell, I hated how the college process reduced my character down into 500 word essays, lists of extracurricular activities, grades, and SAT scores. I kept wondering how colleges could ever make informed decisions about who to accept if the information they were using was so lacking, so single-dimensional, so seemingly ineffective at accomplishing colleges’ goals of creating diverse and thoughtful communities.</p>

<p>This way of assessing high schoolers has resulted in a robotic, artificially structured approach to school. We all know more than a few students who attempt to engineer their application to perfection. Their summers are spent doing hundreds of hours of community service not as an opportunity to help others but as a way to list off another achievement. Their academic career is not spent enjoying the profound personal value of learning, but wasted trying to average a number as close to 5.0 as possible. Though this is most prevalent in high school, I see it perpetuated by parents more and more in younger kids. My friend tutors a 7th grader whose parents have already brought her and her younger sibling to tour Harvard. When told that this tutor was attending Yale next year, she excitedly exclaims “Oh! That’s an Ivy!” This is not what education should be, especially during some of the most impressionable and developmental years of youth.</p>

<p>This problematic mentality is exactly what McCullough warns us against when he recites, “You’re not special.” He uses the word “special” to indicate a false sense of worth founded more on prestige than on meaningful achievement. He states:</p>

<blockquote><p>“…we have of late, we Americans, to our detriment, come to love accolades more than genuine achievement.  We have come to see them as the point – and we’re happy to compromise standards, or ignore reality, if we suspect that’s the quickest way, or only way, to have something to put on the mantelpiece, something to pose with, crow about, something with which to leverage ourselves into a better spot on the social totem pole.”</p>

<p> </p></blockquote>

<p>How can he be more clear than that? We “love accolades more than genuine achievement.” He is by no means trying to diminish the standards or weaken the ambition of us graduating seniors. Instead he urges us to strive for something much greater than what we are used to striving for in high school, to struggle for things without the hope of being recognized, to raise our standards above the objective and bravely enter the realm where all goals must be subjectively determined.</p>

<p>No, he is not being unrealistic. He is not advocating a world completely devoid of the need for grades and rankings and job positions. What McCullough puts forth is a vision of a <em>personal</em> paradigm, a way for the individual to see the world. The fact that GPA’s will always exist does not prevent me from realizing that a GPA speaks little about my passionate desire to learn. The fact that six digit salaries will always be competed for does not mean that they are my ultimate ambition. The balance between <em>need</em> and <em>want</em> can only be achieved if one’s true hopes and dreams are kept alive.</p>

<p>I think Mr. McCullough’s message is one that needs to be heard all over America. Students and parents from all walks of life need to hear his message: “Climb the mountain not to plant your flag, but to embrace the challenge, enjoy the air and behold the view.  Climb it so you can see the world, not so the world can see you,” because put simply, the real possibilities of life exceed infinitely beyond objective standards. As a matter of principle, living a fulfilling life demands the pursuit of true meaning and happiness as it pertains to the individual.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mr. McCullough&#8217;s 2012 Commencement Speech]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/06/mr-mcculloughs-2012-commencement-speech/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/06/mr-mcculloughs-2012-commencement-speech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>*After a compelling and rather stern speech by our principal Dr. Keough about the importance of integrity and honesty during my graduation exercises at Wellesley High School, Mr. McCullough, an English teacher, gave a speech that had the audience roaring with laughter and nodding with understanding. His speech lifted our spirits and gave me something to ponder this summer. As I think about my future in all its glorious and frightening uncertainty, Mr. McCullough’s words remind me of what is most important, that “the great and curious truth of the human experience is that selflessness is the best thing you can do for yourself.” He refers to selflessness in the altruistic sense but also to convey the idea that the individual should not treat himself as an end, but rather, as a source. Using the mountain climber analogy, one should “Climb it so you can see the world, not so the world can see you.” This message resonated the strongest with me, the idea that life is lived best through relentless and active “pursuit,” of what is meaningful and applying one’s identity as the ultimate judge of what is worth living for and what isn’t.
Update: <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=_lfxYhtf8o4">Here</a> is the speech on Youtube.</p>

<p>___|\<em>__|\</em>__|\<em>__|\</em>__|\<em>__|\</em>__|\<em>__|\</em>__|\<em>__|\</em>__|\<em>__|\</em>__|\<em>__|\</em>__|\<em>__|\</em>__|\<em>__|\</em>__|</p>

<p><em>“</em>Dr. Wong, Dr. Keough, Mrs. Novogroski, Ms. Curran, members of the board of education, family and friends of the graduates, ladies and gentlemen of the Wellesley High School class of 2012, for the privilege of speaking to you this afternoon, I am honored and grateful.  Thank you.</p>

<p>So here we are… commencement… life’s great forward-looking ceremony.  (And don’t say, “What about weddings?”  Weddings are one-sided and insufficiently effective.  Weddings are bride-centric pageantry.  Other than conceding to a list of unreasonable demands, the groom just stands there.  No stately, hey-everybody-look-at-me procession.  No being given away.  No identity-changing pronouncement.  And can you imagine a television show dedicated to watching guys try on tuxedos?  Their fathers sitting there misty-eyed with joy and disbelief, their brothers lurking in the corner muttering with envy.  Left to men, weddings would be, after limits-testing procrastination, spontaneous, almost inadvertent… during halftime… on the way to the refrigerator.  And then there’s the frequency of failure: statistics tell us half of you will get divorced.  A winning percentage like that’ll get you last place in the American League East.  The Baltimore Orioles do better than weddings.)</p>

<p>But this ceremony… commencement… a commencement works every time.  From this day forward… truly… in sickness and in health, through financial fiascos, through midlife crises and passably attractive sales reps at trade shows in Cincinnati, through diminishing tolerance for annoyingness, through every difference, irreconcilable and otherwise, you will stay forever graduated from high school, you and your diploma as one, ’til death do you part.</p>

<p>No, commencement is life’s great ceremonial beginning, with its own attendant and highly appropriate symbolism.  Fitting, for example, for this auspicious rite of passage, is where we find ourselves this afternoon, the venue.  Normally, I avoid clichés like the plague, wouldn’t touch them with a ten-foot pole, but here we are on a literal level playing field.  That matters.  That says something.  And your ceremonial costume… shapeless, uniform, one-size-fits-all.  Whether male or female, tall or short, scholar or slacker, spray-tanned prom queen or intergalactic X-Box assassin, each of you is dressed, you’ll notice, exactly the same.  And your diploma… but for your name, exactly the same.</p>

<p>All of this is as it should be, because none of you is special.</p>

<p>You are not special.  You are not exceptional.</p>

<p>Contrary to what your u9 soccer trophy suggests, your glowing seventh grade report card, despite every assurance of a certain corpulent purple dinosaur, that nice Mister Rogers and your batty Aunt Sylvia, no matter how often your maternal caped crusader has swooped in to save you… you’re nothing special.</p>

<p>Yes, you’ve been pampered, cosseted, doted upon, helmeted, bubble-wrapped.  Yes, capable adults with other things to do have held you, kissed you, fed you, wiped your mouth, wiped your bottom, trained you, taught you, tutored you, coached you, listened to you, counseled you, encouraged you, consoled you and encouraged you again.  You’ve been nudged, cajoled, wheedled and implored.  You’ve been feted and fawned over and called sweetie pie.  Yes, you have.  And, certainly, we’ve been to your games, your plays, your recitals, your science fairs.  Absolutely, smiles ignite when you walk into a room, and hundreds gasp with delight at your every tweet.  Why, maybe you’ve even had your picture in the Townsman!  [Editor&#8217;s upgrade: Or The Swellesley Report!] And now you’ve conquered high school… and, indisputably, here we all have gathered for you, the pride and joy of this fine community, the first to emerge from that magnificent new building…</p>

<p>But do not get the idea you’re anything special.  Because you’re not.</p>

<p>The empirical evidence is everywhere, numbers even an English teacher can’t ignore.  Newton, Natick, Nee… I am allowed to say Needham, yes? …that has to be two thousand high school graduates right there, give or take, and that’s just the neighborhood Ns.  Across the country no fewer than 3.2 million seniors are graduating about now from more than 37,000 high schools.  That’s 37,000 valedictorians… 37,000 class presidents… 92,000 harmonizing altos… 340,000 swaggering jocks… 2,185,967 pairs of Uggs.  But why limit ourselves to high school?  After all, you’re leaving it.  So think about this: even if you’re one in a million, on a planet of 6.8 billion that means there are nearly 7,000 people just like you.  Imagine standing somewhere over there on Washington Street on Marathon Monday and watching sixty-eight hundred yous go running by.  And consider for a moment the bigger picture: your planet, I’ll remind you, is not the center of its solar system, your solar system is not the center of its galaxy, your galaxy is not the center of the universe.  In fact, astrophysicists assure us the universe has no center; therefore, you cannot be it.  Neither can Donald Trump… which someone should tell him… although that hair is quite a phenomenon.</p>

<p>“But, Dave,” you cry, “Walt Whitman tells me I’m my own version of perfection!  Epictetus tells me I have the spark of Zeus!”  And I don’t disagree.  So that makes 6.8 billion examples of perfection, 6.8 billion sparks of Zeus.  You see, if everyone is special, then no one is.  If everyone gets a trophy, trophies become meaningless.  In our unspoken but not so subtle Darwinian competition with one another-which springs, I think, from our fear of our own insignificance, a subset of our dread of mortality – we have of late, we Americans, to our detriment, come to love accolades more than genuine achievement.  We have come to see them as the point – and we’re happy to compromise standards, or ignore reality, if we suspect that’s the quickest way, or only way, to have something to put on the mantelpiece, something to pose with, crow about, something with which to leverage ourselves into a better spot on the social totem pole.  No longer is it how you play the game, no longer is it even whether you win or lose, or learn or grow, or enjoy yourself doing it…  Now it’s “So what does this get me?”  As a consequence, we cheapen worthy endeavors, and building a Guatemalan medical clinic becomes more about the application to Bowdoin than the well-being of Guatemalans.  It’s an epidemic – and in its way, not even dear old Wellesley High is immune… one of the best of the 37,000 nationwide, Wellesley High School… where good is no longer good enough, where a B is the new C, and the midlevel curriculum is called Advanced College Placement.  And I hope you caught me when I said “one of the best.”  I said “one of the best” so we can feel better about ourselves, so we can bask in a little easy distinction, however vague and unverifiable, and count ourselves among the elite, whoever they might be, and enjoy a perceived leg up on the perceived competition.  But the phrase defies logic.  By definition there can be only one best.  You’re it or you’re not.</p>

<p>If you’ve learned anything in your years here I hope it’s that education should be for, rather than material advantage, the exhilaration of learning.  You’ve learned, too, I hope, as Sophocles assured us, that wisdom is the chief element of happiness.  (Second is ice cream…  just an fyi)  I also hope you’ve learned enough to recognize how little you know… how little you know now… at the moment… for today is just the beginning.  It’s where you go from here that matters.</p>

<p>As you commence, then, and before you scatter to the winds, I urge you to do whatever you do for no reason other than you love it and believe in its importance.  Don’t bother with work you don’t believe in any more than you would a spouse you’re not crazy about, lest you too find yourself on the wrong side of a Baltimore Orioles comparison.  Resist the easy comforts of complacency, the specious glitter of materialism, the narcotic paralysis of self-satisfaction.  Be worthy of your advantages.  And read… read all the time… read as a matter of principle, as a matter of self-respect.  Read as a nourishing staple of life.  Develop and protect a moral sensibility and demonstrate the character to apply it.  Dream big.  Work hard.  Think for yourself.  Love everything you love, everyone you love, with all your might.  And do so, please, with a sense of urgency, for every tick of the clock subtracts from fewer and fewer; and as surely as there are commencements there are cessations, and you’ll be in no condition to enjoy the ceremony attendant to that eventuality no matter how delightful the afternoon.</p>

<p>The fulfilling life, the distinctive life, the relevant life, is an achievement, not something that will fall into your lap because you’re a nice person or mommy ordered it from the caterer.  You’ll note the founding fathers took pains to secure your inalienable right to life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness-quite an active verb, “pursuit”-which leaves, I should think, little time for lying around watching parrots rollerskate on Youtube.  The first President Roosevelt, the old rough rider, advocated the strenuous life.  Mr. Thoreau wanted to drive life into a corner, to live deep and suck out all the marrow.  The poet Mary Oliver tells us to row, row into the swirl and roil.  Locally, someone… I forget who… from time to time encourages young scholars to carpe the heck out of the diem.  The point is the same: get busy, have at it.  Don’t wait for inspiration or passion to find you.  Get up, get out, explore, find it yourself, and grab hold with both hands.  (Now, before you dash off and get your YOLO tattoo, let me point out the illogic of that trendy little expression-because you can and should live not merely once, but every day of your life.  Rather than You Only Live Once, it should be You Live Only Once… but because YLOO doesn’t have the same ring, we shrug and decide it doesn’t matter.)</p>

<p>None of this day-seizing, though, this YLOOing, should be interpreted as license for self-indulgence.  Like accolades ought to be, the fulfilled life is a consequence, a gratifying byproduct.  It’s what happens when you’re thinking about more important things.  Climb the mountain not to plant your flag, but to embrace the challenge, enjoy the air and behold the view.  Climb it so you can see the world, not so the world can see you.  Go to Paris to be in Paris, not to cross it off your list and congratulate yourself for being worldly.  Exercise free will and creative, independent thought not for the satisfactions they will bring you, but for the good they will do others, the rest of the 6.8 billion-and those who will follow them.  And then you too will discover the great and curious truth of the human experience is that selflessness is the best thing you can do for yourself.  The sweetest joys of life, then, come only with the recognition that you’re not special.</p>

<p>Because everyone is.</p>

<p>Congratulations.  Good luck.  Make for yourselves, please, for your sake and for ours, extraordinary lives.”</p>

<p>**- David McCullough, June 1st 2012</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on Metaphilosophy: The Role of Philosophy in My Life]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/05/reflections-on-metaphilosophy-the-role-of-philosophy-in-my-life/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/05/reflections-on-metaphilosophy-the-role-of-philosophy-in-my-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I wish I could say that I had a sudden realization, some profound epiphany concerning the human condition. It would be more thrilling for the reader. Unfortunately, the insights that I have reached through philosophy usually come about through a much more gradual, much less dramatic process. In compelling me to alter my understanding and interpretation of the world, the process can be dauntingly uncertain and even painful. I consider this very process of critical thought “philosophy.” But before I continue, I must clarify the meaning of this word. By philosophy, I mean the process of thinking, perceiving, and judging oneself and the world rationally in accordance with empirical knowledge. Philosophy also refers to the study of general and fundamental problems concerning truth, ethics, and human existence. I will address both in this essay. Nowadays people tend to have a negative conception of philosophy. The word invokes images of grand ivory towers situated behind ivy walls. Inside the towers in an oak-paneled room a pretentious old man sits on a gilded armchair, living in luxurious decadence. Out of touch with real world issues and having never encountered adversity, he spends his time contemplating ideas to amuse his intellect. This is not philosophy. In my experience, even educated people frequently misconceive of philosophy as an esoterically useless discipline meant only for an intelligentsia out of touch with the world. Among university students for instance, philosophy is one of the most ridiculed majors, right next to art history and English literature. This attitude towards philosophy has always infuriated me, not only because it shows the underlying ignorance of the believer, but also because of its glaring irony. The course of my life thus far has led me to firmly believe that philosophy is the most practical and necessary of all human disciplines.</p>

<p>I did not always believe in philosophy. In fact, I did not even know what philosophy was until sometime during my sophomore year of high school. Rather than being introduced to it or stumbling upon it by chance, I was eventually led to philosophy by my intellectual curiosity. In every class, as soon as I questioned the material on a deep enough level, the same type of apparently unanswerable questions would keep recurring. Biology class defined life as a series of ongoing chemical reactions and suggested that consciousness is the mere exchange of sodium and potassium ions across gated protein channels in the brain. In questioning these definitions, I hit upon philosophical discussions of defining human life, the existence the Platonic soul, and the existence of free will. In English class, reading Hamlet compelled me to consider the ethics of suicide and the possibility of living a meaningful existence despite life’s inevitable tragedies. Even math class, during our study of the summation of infinite series, caused me to contemplate the idea of infinity and the limits of the human mind in conceptualizing the infinite. These are but a few examples in the myriad questions I struggled with during high school.</p>

<p>As I began to systematically contemplate each of these questions, I noticed how they converged and oftentimes complemented one another. The debate about the existence of a soul coincides directly with the god debate. The discussion about free will relates to the ethics of suicide. Thus, not only does philosophy underlie the various academic subjects, but it ties everything together. It acts as a sort of interdisciplinary network, allowing me to synthesize information from one area with that of another. This synthesis allows me to produce conclusions, useful facts which I use to make decisions. In real life, decisions rarely require only a single area of knowledge. All human decisions necessitate thinking about various issues that branch into science, humanities, and other areas of thought. So in a sense, philosophy better prepares me to make real life decisions by making sense of knowledge in the context of all other types of knowledge. It is self-evident that no knowledge has any useful application unless it is contextualized with knowledge from other areas.</p>

<p>I have just discussed the importance of philosophy in the academic realm, but philosophy also exists as a powerful way of thinking. The German philosopher Nietzsche states, “There are no facts, only interpretations.” Apart from the debate of the possibility of absolute truth, there exists the simple fact that interpretation is a necessary and integral part of human perception. One might ask, “What about the objective truths derived from math and science?” I am referring to perception with the intent of applying the information. Of course the fact “one plus one equals two” leaves no room for interpretation. But to make use of it one must interpret this fact in the context of a real life situation. For instance, does falling in love and marrying somebody mean that the two of you exist as a single entity? Or do you both exist separately? What degree of agency should each retain in such a relationship? These questions depend on the understanding that quantities change when combined, but the meaning of such a fact must still be interpreted. In other words, although there are definite facts about the physical nature of the world, these are not truths in the strictly human sense. Knowing one plus one equals two does not inform us on how we should think about ourselves and the world. Hard facts must be interpreted, or humanized, in such a way that allows them to be applied to our lives. It is through this very process of human interpretation that we construct our reality. Philosophy refines the way one interprets the information he receives. The philosophical approach to interpretation entails constantly thinking about external information and cross-referencing it with other facts, with the ultimate goal of reaching a useful and informed conclusion. By approaching the world with a severely critical eye that questions every iota of information it receives, one can reach the most objective conception of the given situation. This involves understanding the various internal biases of both the information giver and receiver. As discussed above, humans operate based on interpretation, not hard fact. No matter how hard they try to give an objective account, it is necessarily influenced by subjective interpretation. Furthermore, one’s own reception of information is unavoidably skewed by internal biases. People often bend things to hear what they want. Philosophy works to counter this two sided subjectivity, allowing one to reach the most objective reality. I had to steel myself with this mentality during the college search process.</p>

<p>Every year during the summer and fall, colleges unleash impressively aggravating advertising campaigns involving tons of paper, emails, and phone calls. In its wake lie acres of deforestation, overflowing spam folders, and millions of poor misled students. Colleges like to personally address the letters to students by first name, writing in a friendly tone hoping to draw them in. They use numbers to boast about the number of Nobel prizes their faculty have received, their annual endowment, and the racial diversity of the student body. They present their institution as alone possessing these characteristics, existing as the most perfect place in the world for you to spend the next four years. I can imagine how the unsuspecting high school junior can easily get lassoed by this type of advertising. In order to find a truly well-fitting college, I approached the process fully aware of the marketing strategies these institutions employed. Furthermore, I understood that the colleges I was applying to are essentially similar with regards to academic quality, diversity of student body, and social atmosphere, differing only in location and other minor characteristics. This approach, I would imagine, spared me the stress of desperately wanting to be accepted to the only college I thought would suit me. I realized that I was applying to a number of colleges I would be very happy at, and that in the end, the experience will depend more on how I use the institution’s resources rather than what resources it provided me. By attaining the most objective reality of the situation, I was able to create the most beneficial interpretation.</p>

<p>Part of interpreting a fact includes determining how valuable that fact is. As humans, we live our lives doing, or with the hope of doing, what we want. We only want what matters to us, what is meaningful and what is valuable. Philosophy aids me on this quest for existential meaning because what I care about is often not easily apparent. It requires a combination of life experiences and deep contemplation to realize what I truly care about. I’m not talking about simple pleasures which can be discovered through reflexive emotional responses. Watching an entertaining movie makes me happy, but the happiness is also shallow and temporary. Simple thrills do not motivate me in the long run. What makes life worth living is the promise of experiencing true, lasting meaning. For instance, it took me many years to fully appreciate my musical education. I always hated practicing and listening to jazz and classical music when I was younger. Now, listening and playing such music gives me a feeling of satisfaction that I don’t get from anything else. Although this may have been a result of my acclimation to music after studying it for so many years, I think the full explanation must acknowledge the fact that I tried to understand and relate to the meaning behind the music. After eight years of study, I know with certainty that I value jazz and classical music on the deepest level.</p>

<p>Having a philosophical state of mind means constantly questioning not only the accuracy of one’s perceptions but also the quality of one’s valuations. It is easy to convince yourself that you enjoy something you actually don’t. Although I have no experience with this, my older brother David shared his experience in the job market and the realizations he’s come to. He told me about how fresh college graduates are frequently misled by jobs with high salaries, not considering the value of the work itself. After graduating, my brother was offered jobs by banks and consulting firms with impressive salaries, but these were jobs that didn’t interest him. Instead he chose to explore the tech-startup industry, working for smaller groups with more modest salaries and lacking the financial benefits of large corporations. Because of this, he’s discovered a passion for computer programming and web development, something he never would’ve been exposed to had he decided to work for a bank. I’m sure that many adults find themselves in the doldrums of a job they hate, realizing after many miserable years that the salary does not outweigh the negatives of the work itself. This can be avoided if one always knows and prioritizes what he deeply values. Through this rationalization, one can easily conclude that money should be treated as a means, not as an end. Philosophy can help one realize that it is not money that is valuable, but rather the possibilities that money provides. By constantly reevaluating my values, I emerge with a more absolute and profound awareness of what is meaningful to me. Philosophy acts as an intellectual sieve, filtering out the refuse and ensuring that what remains is truly valuable to oneself.</p>

<p>I’ve offered my thoughts on the academic importance of philosophy as well as its personal importance in attaining the most objective conception of the world and in striving for true meaning. But the question still remains, what is philosophy? Defining it is difficult because it exists in so many different forms and contexts. In the broadest sense, I consider philosophy an intellectual process which uses reason to investigate and interpret the nature of oneself, one’s environment, and the relationship of the two. Furthermore, philosophy is an internal mode of thinking that is reliable under all external circumstances. In its most ideal form, philosophy should exist as a universal approach to human problems, from the mundane to the profound. Emphasis is placed on reason because only through systematic logic one can effectively determine consistency and inconsistency, and consequentially, right versus wrong and value versus lack of value. All of this philosophical thinking leads to the ultimate purpose of deciding how to live one’s life.</p>

<p>Only by first evaluating the world and oneself objectively can one then decide how to act, acting being the interface between the self and the environment. Only by first answering the question “What is?” can one answer “What should be?” Everyday life demands decisions from us of varying degrees, compelling us to ask ourselves what is moral and immoral. This dilemma presents itself to me every time I choose to illegally pirate music. On one hand, it’s against the law and could have very serious legal ramifications if caught. On the other hand, the artists of the music I pirate already passed away. Their estates would receive all of the commissions from purchases. Knowing them to be artists in the purest sense, I can comfortably conclude that they would rather want people to be exposed to their musical artistry and genius than for their estates to earn money. This is an example of how philosophy remains essential dealing with the question of “How should I act?” Philosophy rationally organizes one’s knowledge and principles to allow this question to be adequately addressed. Because I am constantly exposed to new situations and gaining new knowledge, my answers to this question constantly fluctuates. It is easy to stop considering new information, unintentionally reverting to an outdated ethical mode. As shown by history, the individual’s failure to update their opinions with new facts can lead to disastrous injustices. I remember feeling deeply disturbed when studying about events like the Holocaust, the Rape of Nanjing, and the My Lai Massacre. How could these things happen? How could human beings commit such terrible atrocities to one another, not only murdering and raping but also torturing and mutilating. What happened to the common sense and rational instinct that should have been screaming for an end? These are unanswered questions which will continue to haunt me. But part of the answer, I think, is the fact that the individuals relinquished their ability to independently reason and valuate. Hannah Arendt says, “The sad truth is that most evil is done by people who never make up their minds to be good or evil.” I agree with her idea of the “banality of evil,” that more often than not, human injustice is a result of a lack of thinking, and consequentially the lack of exercising good will. Evil does not arise from actively sinful perpetrators but rather from passively unthinking and prejudiced bystanders. The philosophical mindset both prevents the individual from succumbing to the prejudices of his own complacent intellect and that of others. The philosopher exists as an active agent promoting active thought and thus spreading active morality.</p>

<p>My life has led me to philosophy not out of choice, but out of necessity. My education and personal experiences demand that I answer questions which require a rigorous type of thinking satisfied only by philosophy. For me, the question that will always remain at the core of my life is “What makes life worth living?” More specifically, what makes my life worth living? All other philosophical questions lead to this one. Inquiries into the nature of the universe, one’s identity, and the proper ethics both depend on and help answer this singular question. It is one which is expressed in the art and literature of every era from every region of the world. Contemplation of this question remains at the core of the fundamental human experience. In this sense, there is a touching element of human tragedy to philosophy, that it paradoxically strives to answer a question that has no objectively definitive answer. There is something inexplicably beautiful and deeply inspiring about this Sisyphean struggle. As a philosopher, I’ve come to realize that one does not attain meaning by simply answering the question conclusively and putting the matter to rest. Rather, meaning is found in the very process of attempting to find an answer. What has made my life worth living are all of the things I’ve experienced during my philosophical quest, from the inspiring to the tragic, from the profound to the mundane, from the beautiful to the grotesque. What makes life worth living is the chance to be a philosopher – the opportunity to engage in this existential dialectic, to experience what it means to be human and to know what it means to be me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Moment of Color]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/01/a-moment-of-color/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/01/a-moment-of-color</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>A square of lucid green flickers against the<br/>
blue sky of a sunny winter day,<br/>
catching my eye as I walk towards the common.</p>

<p>Soon I discover the source of the color<br/>
an old man in a wheelchair covered with rags<br/>
tethering the winds with a fishing pole, unknown Aelous of the city.</p>

<p>I pause to watch but he beckons me<br/>
offering me the reigns and<br/>
together we admire the graceful spontaneous dance.</p>

<p>I wonder if he feels alone<br/>
if old age has crippled his body and mind<br/>
and heart I wonder if I am alone, but suddenly I muse:</p>

<p>We are yesterday’s children playing with the air,</p>

<p>We are tomorrow’s painters coloring the sky,</p>

<p>We are timeless spirits sharing a moment of beauty.</p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>1/26/12</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruminations on a Sunday Morning]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/01/ruminations-on-a-sunday-morning/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/01/ruminations-on-a-sunday-morning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I know the passive impulse of your words,<br/>
feeling righteous like a skyscraper<br/>
grounded in unturned soil, yet nothing<br/>
strives to the sky,<br/>
touches the clouds,<br/>
pierces the veil.</p>

<p>I know the sad submission of your being,<br/>
less disappointing for me than wretched for you.</p>

<p>Nature’s spirit sprints and leaps and flies<br/>
in short it moves.<br/>
Human’s spirit is that and a soul for<br/>
struggle<br/>
For dreaming of moving towards<br/>
impossible dimensions<br/>
Not only scraping skies but forging heavens<br/>
blazing with the<br/>
intense will<br/>
that is<br/>
life.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>1/22/2012</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Frank O&#8217;Hara]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/01/frank-ohara/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/01/frank-ohara</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I first discovered Frank O’Hara while watching Mad Men. The last two stanzas of O’Hara’s poem “Mayakovsky” was recited by Don Draper in this <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9XKN0iZG_4s">expressive, melancholic scene.</a> What first struck me was O’Hara’s language; his verse seemed so alive with motion. A combination of a colloquial tone and elevated artistic discourse created a very satisfying effect for me, something I could at once understand and appreciate as profound. Furthermore, his syntax makes his words dance in a way that I haven’t encountered in other poems. His poems are light and easy to move through, as if affected by a certain smooth coherence.</p>

<p>That is ironic, because his poetry is anything but coherent. Living in the artistic milieu of mid-20th century Manhattan, O’Hara was very much inspired by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abstract_expressionism">Abstract Expressionism.</a> He believed that art itself existed on a transcendent level. So rather than the artist commanding the art, he believed that art commanded the artist. This notion has roots in the Greek idea that inspiration occurs when a God “breathes upon” someone, that humans draw creativity from some higher external source. In this manner, O’Hara believed that all “accidents” in art were meant to be. He let his poems progress rather organically, writing about thoughts and feelings as they spontaneously arrived rather than crafting the poem around a premeditated central theme. Compared to poetry of the previous centuries, this approach is quite new. It is abstract, cerebral, and difficult to understand. But at the same time, his poetry is refreshing, innovative, and above all, beautiful. Here are some of my favorite poems by Frank O’Hara:</p>

<p><strong>POEM</strong></p>

<p>Instant coffee with slightly sour cream<br/>
in it, and a phone call to the beyond<br/>
which doesn’t seem to be coming any nearer.<br/>
“Ah daddy, I wanna stay drunk many days”<br/>
on the poetry of a new friend<br/>
my life held precariously in the seeing<br/>
hands of others, their and my impossibilities.<br/>
Is this love, now that the first love<br/>
has finally died, where there were no impossibilities?</p>

<p><strong>Wind</strong></p>

<p>Who’d have thought<br/>
that snow falls<br/>
it always circled whirling<br/>
like a thought<br/>
in the glass ball<br/>
around me and my bear</p>

<p>Then it seemed beautiful<br/>
containment<br/>
snow whirled<br/>
nothing ever fell<br/>
nor my little bear<br/>
bad thoughts<br/>
imprisoned in crystal</p>

<p>beauty has replaced itself with evil</p>

<p>And the snow whirls only<br/>
in fatal winds<br/>
briefly<br/>
then falls</p>

<p>it always loathed containment<br/>
beasts<br/>
I love evil</p>

<p>Frank O’Hara also wrote one of my favorite quotes: “Simply to live does not justify existence, for life is a mere gesture on the surface of the earth, and death a return to that from which we had never been wholly separated; but oh to leave a trace, no matter how faint, of that brief gesture! For someone, some day, may find it beautiful!”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Response to Hume’s Argument Against the Existence of God]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/01/response-to-hume%e2%80%99s-argument-against-the-existence-of-god/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/01/response-to-hume%e2%80%99s-argument-against-the-existence-of-god</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><em>This is a response to an argument which Hume presents in his “Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion.”</em></p>

<p>Hume bases his dialectic on the idea that knowledge must rest on <em>a posteriori</em> experience rather than faith. This is because empirical evidence is essential to determining the plausibility of one idea over another in defining truth. Without experience ideas “…would all be possible; but, being all equally possible, he would never…give a satisfactory account for his preferring one of them to the rest” (182). Using this system he carefully refutes an <em>a posteriori</em> pro-God argument offered by Cleanthes. Cleanthes argues the existence of God by first asserting the similarity of the universe to a machine, something produced by man’s reason. Then, with the assumption that similar effects implies similar causes, Cleanthes claims that the universe must have been designed by an entity similar to a human being, possessing a similar faculty of thinking. This being is God. Philo dismantles this argument chiefly by attacking the validity of Cleanthes analogy. Philo claims, “Every alteration of circumstances occasions a doubt concerning the event” (183). Because there exists so many differences and unaccounted variables between man’s machines and the entire universe, Cleanthes analogy is unsound. Therefore, God cannot be claimed to exist in this manner. Philo then adds the argument that man’s faculty of reasoning exists as merely “one of the springs of the universe, as well as heat or cold, attraction or repulsion” (184). He equates the cause of thought to all other causes. Therefore, it is unreasonable to project the cause of thought as the ultimate cause of the universe. In his typical fashion, Hume uses skepticism to refute the God argument. Finally, assuming that such a grand analogy could be made, Hume subtly places “generation,” the system of birth observed in animals, as a more probable cause than reason. This is because humans have observed that reason derives from generation, but generation has not been observed to derive from reason. Therefore, generation exists as an earlier cause, thus it is more likely to be the ultimate cause.</p>

<p>Hume’s structured and logically rigorous manner of argument impresses me. The logical progression from one statement to the other appears quite sound. However, I question Hume’s assumption that <em>means</em> adapt to <em>ends</em>. In both Cleanthes and Philo’s arguments, there was a tacit acceptance of this idea without addressing the possibility that <em>ends </em>merely stem from <em>means</em>. What humans observe as the product of design may very well exist as the logical effect of the random arrangement of the universe. What we assume to be means may merely be the product of random chance. For instance, the arrangement of our solar system may have been due to chance rather than some intended cause. Perhaps Hume did not mean to imply this. Nevertheless, he implies a certain directed, or even conscious, <em>intent</em> in his idea of cause. I wish Hume addressed this assumption and clarified the nature of his idea of “cause.” I also question Hume’s seemingly casual relegation of human thinking as one of hundreds of causes. He describes it as “so minute, so weak, so bounded a principle” and “this little agitation of the brain which we call ‘thought’” (184). As a philosopher I believe Hume should hold higher regard for his single most important ability. It seems that he has extended his ideal of skepticism too far. Nevertheless, I consider his dismissal of thought as an interesting idea which could potentially inspire certain other ideas. For this reason, I will continue contemplating it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on the Nature and Importance of Reality]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2011/10/reflections-on-the-nature-and-importance-of-reality/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2011/10/reflections-on-the-nature-and-importance-of-reality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I wrote this partially in response to Lyle Zynda’s “The Nature of Reality and Why It Matters.”</p>

<p><em>Realism</em> is the idea that there exists an objective universe external to the human perception. Realist philosophers believe that the word “real” can refer to something independent of the human senses. What humans perceive may not necessarily constitute the definite, real world. According to one fundamental epistemological argument, humans do not experience reality directly. Rather, we merely perceive our brain’s interpretation of reality. This provides realists significant doubt that reality matches the subjective experience of humans. Furthermore, biologically the human body is only capable of receiving a limited range of sensory data. For instance, we cannot detect electromagnetic fields or perceive infrared radiation like other animals. Even though we don’t experience them directly, our science proves their existence. Therefore, it is possible that humans have a very limited grasp on the true reality.</p>

<p>This debate over the true nature of reality may seem like something whimsical and only for the amusement of dilettantes. Upon further reflection, how an individual decides to approach and answer this ultimately personal question holds enormous stake because it influences the way he conducts his life. Whereas the realist may decide to pursue a life of science in order to uncover what he believes to be an objective truth, a non-realist may decide to follow his instinct because reality is ultimately subjective. The question also deals with hope and imagination. Consider an individual who disagrees with the social norms of his time. If he was a realist, perhaps he would decide to live in contentedness because ultimately the world operates based on higher functions. The non-realist may be galvanized by his belief in the malleable nature of reality, that the status quo is not necessarily the way things have to exist.</p>

<p>Personally, I think this question matters in terms of choosing whether or not to believe in one’s current environment. I question Nozick’s claim that given proper thought, most people would not choose to enter an illusory state. Both Nozick and <em>The Matrix</em> strongly associate living in a dream with dishonor and corruption. I believe that because there is insufficient positive proof in the existence of an objective reality, humans are forced to trust their default, subjective experience. Accepting a subjective reality is not only more logical but preferable. Our senses render everything we experience and our consciousness processes and decides how we react. Humans are unable to step outside of our mind-body complex. Our whole lives are inescapably lived in a subjective manner, whether we believe in an objective reality or not.  Furthermore, what matters and what is meaningful exists as a human question. For all we know, the very concept of “meaning” is man-made. This definition necessitates subjectivity in the human quest for meaning. Therefore, logically I see no philosophical problem with choosing to enter a dream world that is more “perfect” (also a human, subjective concept) than the current world. Why would it matter to escape to a dream, if we weren’t ever aware of its artifice? How do we, as human beings, know for sure that we are not in a dream right now? This in conjunction with the assumption that human experience is subjective suggests the identical nature of the “real” world and the “dream world.” There exists no difference able to be grasped by the human.</p>

<p>In order for me to define what matters to me, I must first decide “What is reality?” For this reason, I will continue to ponder this question as I grow older.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Response to Carl Jung&#8217;s Concept of the Collective Unconscious]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2011/09/response-to-carl-jungs-concept-of-the-collective-unconscious/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2011/09/response-to-carl-jungs-concept-of-the-collective-unconscious</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>For my English class we had to read and respond to an <a href="http://www.carl-jung.net/collective_unconscious.html">interesting article</a>.</p>

<p>Coincidentally, this article formalizes a question I have been pondering for some time now. Is individuality merely an illusion for what is actually uniform throughout all humans? To what degree can humans vary in behavior and belief? Most importantly, do humans behave based on a system of innate formulas and biological patterns? This question holds immense stake because if our thoughts and actions <em>can</em> be defined as preconceived responses, then there is no such thing as free-will. If this is the case, we do not make decisions but rather carry out predetermined responses appropriate to the situation based on the stimuli we receive. But based on the reading, Jung does not extend his idea to such lengths as I have. He is unclear as to what extent the collective unconscious determines human behavior. Viewed like this, Jung’s idea becomes rather commonplace. It seems obvious that there would be similarities in parent-child relationships and the way humans respond to failure.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.google.com/url?source=imglanding&amp;ct=img&amp;q=http://www.metaphysics-for-life.com/images/humanmind.jpg&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=adRrTrDXDqje0QGZ3aHuBA&amp;ved=0CAYQ8wc&amp;usg=AFQjCNFU69xSgfka3KtnjOMQtIGoQb3dAg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Concerning the question I proposed at the beginning, I realize it may unfairly imply a one-sided answer. Human nature may be a combination of both Jung’s collective unconscious, which we have no control over, and individuality, which we do have control over to some extent. Then my question becomes, what is the relationship between the collective unconscious and free will? Is one dependent on the other? What has more influence over our lives?</p>

<p>Jung’s idea compels me to ask if the collective unconscious is stagnant or malleable. Does it exist as something eternal and unchanging? Or, as times progress and human society changes, does the collective unconscious change as well? Perhaps the collective unconscious remains fundamentally the same, but its manifestations change according to its environment. If this is the case, then the eastern tradition of discovering one’s Self will always remain pertinent.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On the Nature of Selfishness]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2011/09/on-the-nature-of-selfishness/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2011/09/on-the-nature-of-selfishness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I’m sure many have encountered the idea that “Communism fails in practice because humans are inherently selfish.” I tend to get annoyed whenever somebody says this (especially if they declare it with an attitude of intellectualism, as if to show off the understanding of an incredibly advanced philosophical concept), for two reasons. First, the saying is cliche. Second, this concept is too easy; it’s an answer that blindly undermines the complexity of human nature. If I wanted to be pompous, I could say that believers of this idea lack a basic understanding of humanity. But, because this contradicts the spirit of the claim itself, I will refrain. In this post, I explore the second reason.</p>

<p>Put simply, I believe selfishness, or egotism, does indeed exist as an intrinsic characteristic of humans, but that there are thresholds, or degrees, of selfishness. Selfishness cannot be represented by any single parable, it does not appear as one color. Rather, it manifests itself in a multitude of ways that, according to its simple definition, may not be perceived as selfishness.</p>

<p>Consider the situation in which a group of high school students found an organization that raises money for a charity. The organization ends up raising a decent amount of money. However, the students’ primary motivation is not that of philanthropy, but to augment their college application. While the integrity and principle of their motives are controversial, the utility of the resulting action removes any doubt of its benefit. It is strange that human selfishness can manifest itself in beneficial actions, one of many seemingly impossible contradictions of ideals that humans are capable of.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.google.com/url?source=imgres&amp;ct=img&amp;q=http://www.corrupt.org/drupal/files/images/help.jpg&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=unAKTrrDDoLw0gGgpuR6&amp;ved=0CAQQ8wc4IQ&amp;usg=AFQjCNGVv2b2PlsZU4Z9XvsfsSz2ETh5PA" alt="" /></p>

<p>As previously mentioned, I think selfishness exists in degrees. The shallowest thresholds of egotism express themselves in the most corrupt ways, in situations able to be categorized as simply “bad.” For instance, murdering for money. On the other hand, the deepest thresholds of selfishness transcend superficially crass motives. Instead, such thresholds are selfishly motivated by metaphysical ideas of justice, love, and empathy. At the deepest levels, humans exhibit a selfishness for preserving their own morality. It is a self-indulgence in being “good,” for few can deny the unparalleled satisfaction from charitable actions. We tend to classify such behavior as “selfless,” but I think altruism is closely connected to the self. Would I be going too far in saying, “Altruism is merely a veiled selfishness?” Perhaps, with an expanded definition of selfishness, the idea is not too far-fetched.</p>

<p>But why understand these dialectics, besides the philosopher’s job of finding consistency to explain ostensibly irrational human behavior? The stake, as I see it, lies in reforming society. I believe the shallower tiers of selfishness can be eliminated through a combination of education and the insurance of survival necessities. There is no necessary provocation for an educated man, who has food, clothes, and shelter, to commit crimes. As the two bottom-most levels of</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
