<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Poetry | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/blog/categories/poetry/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-20T03:11:52-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://yoursite.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Moment of Color]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/01/a-moment-of-color/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/01/a-moment-of-color</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>A square of lucid green flickers against the<br/>
blue sky of a sunny winter day,<br/>
catching my eye as I walk towards the common.</p>

<p>Soon I discover the source of the color<br/>
an old man in a wheelchair covered with rags<br/>
tethering the winds with a fishing pole, unknown Aelous of the city.</p>

<p>I pause to watch but he beckons me<br/>
offering me the reigns and<br/>
together we admire the graceful spontaneous dance.</p>

<p>I wonder if he feels alone<br/>
if old age has crippled his body and mind<br/>
and heart I wonder if I am alone, but suddenly I muse:</p>

<p>We are yesterday’s children playing with the air,</p>

<p>We are tomorrow’s painters coloring the sky,</p>

<p>We are timeless spirits sharing a moment of beauty.</p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>1/26/12</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ruminations on a Sunday Morning]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/01/ruminations-on-a-sunday-morning/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/01/ruminations-on-a-sunday-morning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I know the passive impulse of your words,<br/>
feeling righteous like a skyscraper<br/>
grounded in unturned soil, yet nothing<br/>
strives to the sky,<br/>
touches the clouds,<br/>
pierces the veil.</p>

<p>I know the sad submission of your being,<br/>
less disappointing for me than wretched for you.</p>

<p>Nature’s spirit sprints and leaps and flies<br/>
in short it moves.<br/>
Human’s spirit is that and a soul for<br/>
struggle<br/>
For dreaming of moving towards<br/>
impossible dimensions<br/>
Not only scraping skies but forging heavens<br/>
blazing with the<br/>
intense will<br/>
that is<br/>
life.</p>

<p> </p>

<p>1/22/2012</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Frank O&#8217;Hara]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/01/frank-ohara/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/01/frank-ohara</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>I first discovered Frank O’Hara while watching Mad Men. The last two stanzas of O’Hara’s poem “Mayakovsky” was recited by Don Draper in this <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9XKN0iZG_4s">expressive, melancholic scene.</a> What first struck me was O’Hara’s language; his verse seemed so alive with motion. A combination of a colloquial tone and elevated artistic discourse created a very satisfying effect for me, something I could at once understand and appreciate as profound. Furthermore, his syntax makes his words dance in a way that I haven’t encountered in other poems. His poems are light and easy to move through, as if affected by a certain smooth coherence.</p>

<p>That is ironic, because his poetry is anything but coherent. Living in the artistic milieu of mid-20th century Manhattan, O’Hara was very much inspired by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abstract_expressionism">Abstract Expressionism.</a> He believed that art itself existed on a transcendent level. So rather than the artist commanding the art, he believed that art commanded the artist. This notion has roots in the Greek idea that inspiration occurs when a God “breathes upon” someone, that humans draw creativity from some higher external source. In this manner, O’Hara believed that all “accidents” in art were meant to be. He let his poems progress rather organically, writing about thoughts and feelings as they spontaneously arrived rather than crafting the poem around a premeditated central theme. Compared to poetry of the previous centuries, this approach is quite new. It is abstract, cerebral, and difficult to understand. But at the same time, his poetry is refreshing, innovative, and above all, beautiful. Here are some of my favorite poems by Frank O’Hara:</p>

<p><strong>POEM</strong></p>

<p>Instant coffee with slightly sour cream<br/>
in it, and a phone call to the beyond<br/>
which doesn’t seem to be coming any nearer.<br/>
“Ah daddy, I wanna stay drunk many days”<br/>
on the poetry of a new friend<br/>
my life held precariously in the seeing<br/>
hands of others, their and my impossibilities.<br/>
Is this love, now that the first love<br/>
has finally died, where there were no impossibilities?</p>

<p><strong>Wind</strong></p>

<p>Who’d have thought<br/>
that snow falls<br/>
it always circled whirling<br/>
like a thought<br/>
in the glass ball<br/>
around me and my bear</p>

<p>Then it seemed beautiful<br/>
containment<br/>
snow whirled<br/>
nothing ever fell<br/>
nor my little bear<br/>
bad thoughts<br/>
imprisoned in crystal</p>

<p>beauty has replaced itself with evil</p>

<p>And the snow whirls only<br/>
in fatal winds<br/>
briefly<br/>
then falls</p>

<p>it always loathed containment<br/>
beasts<br/>
I love evil</p>

<p>Frank O’Hara also wrote one of my favorite quotes: “Simply to live does not justify existence, for life is a mere gesture on the surface of the earth, and death a return to that from which we had never been wholly separated; but oh to leave a trace, no matter how faint, of that brief gesture! For someone, some day, may find it beautiful!”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
