<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Listening | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/blog/categories/listening/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-21T21:06:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://yoursite.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brad Mehldau&#8217;s &#8220;My Favorite Things&#8221;]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2013/02/brad-mehldaus-my-favorite-things/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2013/02/brad-mehldaus-my-favorite-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>Jazz musicians and educators always make comparisons between jazz improvisation and language. They talk of expanding one’s “jazz vocabulary” and “pacing” one’s solos effectively. They say that the best solos “tell a story.” In this way, the jazz soloist is analogous a rhetorician giving an improvised speech, attempting saying something meaningful to the audience. But sometimes, as is often the case with many of my favorite recordings, the artist seems engage in a soliloquy, full of introverted reflections. To name off the top of my head some musicians who do this a lot — Miles Davis, Wes Montgomery, and Bill Evans.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><img src="http://i.ytimg.com/vi/gClg7L_vqes/0.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p> </p>

<p>Brad Mehldau’s live recording of “My Favorite Things” is one such recording, and it’s one that means a lot to me both aesthetically and philosophically: the music itself simply sounds beautiful, and the emotions and thoughts it invokes in me are profound. Here is a <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X7fVnvJSRb4">link</a> to the piece.</p>

<p>In an <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/joseph-vella/brad-mehldau-the-art-of-s_b_823026.html">interview</a> with the Huffington Post, Mehldau said:</p>

<blockquote><p>“One fun surprise of this concert was “My Favorite Things.” It was not something I had played before – the Coltrane version is sacred to me. But I was going out for an encore and thought of it at the last moment, and it turned out to be for me anyways, one of the more compelling performances in the set – it had that story to it; it just kind of unfolded. Sometimes you find that and sometimes you don’t; sometimes you find it with no preparation or context at all and those moments are always great for me.”</p></blockquote>

<p>The piece seems even more impressive considering that it was spontaneous. But I guess you can hear that in the recording, how it progresses so naturally from a simple introduction to a compelling climax down to an ending. The recording really does sound like a soliloquy. We seem to be hearing the depths of Mehldau’s consciousness expressed musically. You know, those deep thoughts that exist but remain unknown to us until, in solitude, they gradually become lucid. This happens to me a lot during walks in quiet, peaceful places. For artists, I would imagine it happens during those rare instances of perfect artistic inspiration.</p>

<p>I listen to this piece a lot when I’m feeling melancholic, introverted, thoughtful, nostalgic, or any other feeling that would make me temporarily anti-social and weird. Anyhow, I thought I’d share this piece. Hopefully you hear something in it that you can relate to.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Music as Sound, Sound as Music]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/12/music-as-sound-sound-as-music/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/12/music-as-sound-sound-as-music</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>Leaning forward in my chair, I gripped my saxophone in anticipation. It was my first rehearsal with the Senior Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, the first musical group to ever intimidate me with its degree of talent and level of perfection. Widely regarded as one of the top wind ensembles in the world, the group is led by Michael Mucci — a conductor, educator, and mentor whom I admire deeply. During his opening remarks he said a curious thing.</p>

<p>“You are all here because you love sound.”</p>

<p>Strange, I thought. Why would he use the word sound? In my mind, the word “sound” stood uncomfortable close to “noise.” I wasn’t just producing mere sounds; I was making music — an art that requires skill and refinement, an art that is the opposite of noise. But for some reason, his words remained in the back of my mind and their meaning grew clearer as I matured musically through my high school years. Before this, however, I had to learn that listening to music is just as much a craft as making music.I didn’t always know how to listen to music well, and I still have a lot to learn. I remember how teachers would recommend that I listen to recordings like Miles Davis’ Kind of Blue and John Coltrane’s A Love Supreme, and how I would get bored after a few minutes. I thought it was because I didn’t understand the music theory underlying the jazz. But after devoting much time to learning about chord progressions and two-fives and secondary dominants, I still could not enjoy these records. Understanding that the tune “So What” has a modal structure that modulates up a half step in the bridge did not help me at all in appreciating the track.</p>

<p>Eventually, I was introduced to the concept of tone. Teachers emphasized the importance of developing a unique sound, asking me questions like “How would you describe your sound?” Dark, rounded, and pure, I would say. I knew that good tone was an important aspect of musicianship, but I hadn’t thought about it as something up to the musician to define. Miles Davis was always championed as having the quintessentially unique voice, so I began paying more attention to the way his trumpet sounded, not just the notes he played. With this attitude of listening for how things sounded holistically rather than how the notes were arranged, I gave Kind of Blue another shot. This time, I found myself able to sit through the full nine minutes of each track with a sustained interest. Instead of fixating on that particular bluesy lick that Cannonball played or the pentatonic scale that Coltrane used, I focused on how the richness of Bill Evan’s chords complemented Miles’ subdued tone. I noticed the contrast between the distinct sounds of Coltrane, Cannonball, and Miles, and how that lent the album a mosaic-like quality. I absorbed the recording’s general chilled, quiet, impressionistic ethos. I could go on about what I love about the album, but the point is that a simple shift in my listener’s attitude was all that I needed to understand the music. Studying jazz theory was unnecessary because listening to music involves something much more fundamental — it involves the skill of listening to sound.</p>

<p>I approached both new and familiar pieces of music with this new philosophy, asking the question: What kinds of sounds are these artists attempting to create? Sound, of course, gets conveyed in many different forms. In jazz, for example, the artist’s phrasing, tone, dynamics, intonation, rhythmic and melodic choices all characterize his sound. In classical, the composer’s orchestration and compositional choices as well as the performer’s interpretive choices comprise the sound. With this attitude, I listened with more focus; with more attention to subtle nuances and with more awareness of the piece as a whole. The result was that I appreciated a greater variety of music to a greater degree. Intrigued by new and unfamiliar sounds, I was less inclined to avoid music whose style wasn’t immediately familiar to me. That being said, I was not able to simply dive into the avant-garde. But I was able to immerse myself in the sound of a lesser-known, more unique composer such as Mahler or Tord Gustavsen.</p>

<p>And at its very core, music is just this — sound. After the last chord of every concert with the Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, my heart raced and my mind marveled at how magnificently the sound reverberated throughout the concert hall — entire seconds of sustained acoustic glory. The audience seemed to be equally mesmerized, remaining silent for a few seconds after the note had died out before applause broke out. A friend of mine went to one such concert and said to me afterwards, “The concert was amazing! Especially that last piece, there was just so much sound coming from all directions.” He had never studied music before and was able to enjoy a classical concert. Most people think jazz and classical music, or any type of non-pop music, are esoteric art forms, inaccessible to those who are untrained and inexperienced. But my near decade of intensive musical training and experience has only made me realize that this isn’t the case. Music is not about mastering the technicalities of a particular genre and being able to play specific notes in a specific style in a specific order. Music is about developing and expressing our natural, human instinct to produce different sounds and appreciate how they interact and combine in beautiful ways.</p>

<p>Later, my new understanding of music changed the way I hear everything around me, not just sounds in the concert hall or the practice room. Being a musician naturally made me more sensitive to any sound at all, and this came at a cost. For instance, when someone on my floor forgets to turn off their alarm and I’m in my room, struggling to write a paper, unable to ignore its constant blaring. Or when on a weekend morning the sound of a dozen high-powered leaf blowers, all humming at a slightly off-tune pitch, wakes me up from my lazy sleep. And try as I might, I simply cannot soundproof my room from the commotion that inevitably fills Old Campus every weekend night: drunken yelling, piercing screeches, blaring music, and senseless whoops. For someone who prefers quiet, being so hearing-sensitive makes Yale a very loud place indeed.</p>

<p>But then again, a heightened awareness of sounds can be refreshing. Now, sitting by an open window during summer nights, I am able to enjoy the concert of crickets — a cacophony during which polyrhythms emerge and evolve through a series of interlocking rhythms and pitches. And I love when the rich and dissonant call of a train echoes through the quietness of the weekday night, each time with a different blend of notes. My walk these days in the woods can be transformed into something memorable when a particularly lyrical bird sings a song. The ability to hear — to really hear — the sounds of the outside world adds a deeper dimension to my experiences. A memory of a trip to New York City would be incomplete without recalling the chaotic urban sounds of car honks, footsteps, and crowded murmuring. A climb to the summit of a mountain would be diminished without noticing the utterly imposing silence.</p>

<p>Learning to hear music as sound taught me how to hear sound as music. After all, music and sound are not separate realms, and neither are the concert hall and the city streets. It is all part of one single sonic environment that our ears inhabit. So the next time you are in the mood for music, try something new; maybe put on Kind of Blue. If you are feeling adventurous the next time you are out and about, try listening to the world as a recording studio full of new and experimental sounds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Search For Peace – Mccoy Tyner]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/11/search-for-peace-mccoy-tyner/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/11/search-for-peace-mccoy-tyner</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><img src="http://www.lobosenbolos.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/mccoytyner.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I’ve always had this album in my collection because it’s one of those “classic” Blue Note albums, but I never gotten around to listening to it, except maybe once or twice when I had to study the tune “Contemplation.” One track on this record stands out to me — “Search For Peace” — and I’ve been listening to it non-stop. Besides the flawless playing of four jazz legends, I love the song as a composition. I rarely encounter pieces that sound more structurally complex than their actual form, in this case a standard AABA. I like the modal-esque bridge and the three ii/V’s modulating down half a step in the last four bars of the A section.</p>

<p>The track echoes the spiritual ethos that defined much of Coltrane’s music. That’s no surprise, given that Tyner played with Coltrane and recorded with him on many landmark recordings (The Love Supreme, for instance). However, the recording has much more space and subtlety than Coltrane’s music. Compare “Search for Peace” with Coltrane’s “Central Park West” and you will know what I mean.</p>

<p>But music jargon aside, it’s a great recording — one of those pieces that both jazz connoisseurs and casual listeners can appreciate. I’d even venture to say that it’s a timeless recording, like any of the tracks on Kind of Blue, that offers something different upon each new listen.</p>

<p>Do yourself a favor and <a href="http://open.spotify.com/track/4qRJ7ZJyfzchEd2fjle7Bz">listen to the song.</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
