<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Essays | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/blog/categories/essays/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-19T21:13:48-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://yoursite.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Music as Sound, Sound as Music]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/12/music-as-sound-sound-as-music/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/12/music-as-sound-sound-as-music</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>Leaning forward in my chair, I gripped my saxophone in anticipation. It was my first rehearsal with the Senior Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, the first musical group to ever intimidate me with its degree of talent and level of perfection. Widely regarded as one of the top wind ensembles in the world, the group is led by Michael Mucci — a conductor, educator, and mentor whom I admire deeply. During his opening remarks he said a curious thing.</p>

<p>“You are all here because you love sound.”</p>

<p>Strange, I thought. Why would he use the word sound? In my mind, the word “sound” stood uncomfortable close to “noise.” I wasn’t just producing mere sounds; I was making music — an art that requires skill and refinement, an art that is the opposite of noise. But for some reason, his words remained in the back of my mind and their meaning grew clearer as I matured musically through my high school years. Before this, however, I had to learn that listening to music is just as much a craft as making music.I didn’t always know how to listen to music well, and I still have a lot to learn. I remember how teachers would recommend that I listen to recordings like Miles Davis’ Kind of Blue and John Coltrane’s A Love Supreme, and how I would get bored after a few minutes. I thought it was because I didn’t understand the music theory underlying the jazz. But after devoting much time to learning about chord progressions and two-fives and secondary dominants, I still could not enjoy these records. Understanding that the tune “So What” has a modal structure that modulates up a half step in the bridge did not help me at all in appreciating the track.</p>

<p>Eventually, I was introduced to the concept of tone. Teachers emphasized the importance of developing a unique sound, asking me questions like “How would you describe your sound?” Dark, rounded, and pure, I would say. I knew that good tone was an important aspect of musicianship, but I hadn’t thought about it as something up to the musician to define. Miles Davis was always championed as having the quintessentially unique voice, so I began paying more attention to the way his trumpet sounded, not just the notes he played. With this attitude of listening for how things sounded holistically rather than how the notes were arranged, I gave Kind of Blue another shot. This time, I found myself able to sit through the full nine minutes of each track with a sustained interest. Instead of fixating on that particular bluesy lick that Cannonball played or the pentatonic scale that Coltrane used, I focused on how the richness of Bill Evan’s chords complemented Miles’ subdued tone. I noticed the contrast between the distinct sounds of Coltrane, Cannonball, and Miles, and how that lent the album a mosaic-like quality. I absorbed the recording’s general chilled, quiet, impressionistic ethos. I could go on about what I love about the album, but the point is that a simple shift in my listener’s attitude was all that I needed to understand the music. Studying jazz theory was unnecessary because listening to music involves something much more fundamental — it involves the skill of listening to sound.</p>

<p>I approached both new and familiar pieces of music with this new philosophy, asking the question: What kinds of sounds are these artists attempting to create? Sound, of course, gets conveyed in many different forms. In jazz, for example, the artist’s phrasing, tone, dynamics, intonation, rhythmic and melodic choices all characterize his sound. In classical, the composer’s orchestration and compositional choices as well as the performer’s interpretive choices comprise the sound. With this attitude, I listened with more focus; with more attention to subtle nuances and with more awareness of the piece as a whole. The result was that I appreciated a greater variety of music to a greater degree. Intrigued by new and unfamiliar sounds, I was less inclined to avoid music whose style wasn’t immediately familiar to me. That being said, I was not able to simply dive into the avant-garde. But I was able to immerse myself in the sound of a lesser-known, more unique composer such as Mahler or Tord Gustavsen.</p>

<p>And at its very core, music is just this — sound. After the last chord of every concert with the Massachusetts Youth Wind Ensemble, my heart raced and my mind marveled at how magnificently the sound reverberated throughout the concert hall — entire seconds of sustained acoustic glory. The audience seemed to be equally mesmerized, remaining silent for a few seconds after the note had died out before applause broke out. A friend of mine went to one such concert and said to me afterwards, “The concert was amazing! Especially that last piece, there was just so much sound coming from all directions.” He had never studied music before and was able to enjoy a classical concert. Most people think jazz and classical music, or any type of non-pop music, are esoteric art forms, inaccessible to those who are untrained and inexperienced. But my near decade of intensive musical training and experience has only made me realize that this isn’t the case. Music is not about mastering the technicalities of a particular genre and being able to play specific notes in a specific style in a specific order. Music is about developing and expressing our natural, human instinct to produce different sounds and appreciate how they interact and combine in beautiful ways.</p>

<p>Later, my new understanding of music changed the way I hear everything around me, not just sounds in the concert hall or the practice room. Being a musician naturally made me more sensitive to any sound at all, and this came at a cost. For instance, when someone on my floor forgets to turn off their alarm and I’m in my room, struggling to write a paper, unable to ignore its constant blaring. Or when on a weekend morning the sound of a dozen high-powered leaf blowers, all humming at a slightly off-tune pitch, wakes me up from my lazy sleep. And try as I might, I simply cannot soundproof my room from the commotion that inevitably fills Old Campus every weekend night: drunken yelling, piercing screeches, blaring music, and senseless whoops. For someone who prefers quiet, being so hearing-sensitive makes Yale a very loud place indeed.</p>

<p>But then again, a heightened awareness of sounds can be refreshing. Now, sitting by an open window during summer nights, I am able to enjoy the concert of crickets — a cacophony during which polyrhythms emerge and evolve through a series of interlocking rhythms and pitches. And I love when the rich and dissonant call of a train echoes through the quietness of the weekday night, each time with a different blend of notes. My walk these days in the woods can be transformed into something memorable when a particularly lyrical bird sings a song. The ability to hear — to really hear — the sounds of the outside world adds a deeper dimension to my experiences. A memory of a trip to New York City would be incomplete without recalling the chaotic urban sounds of car honks, footsteps, and crowded murmuring. A climb to the summit of a mountain would be diminished without noticing the utterly imposing silence.</p>

<p>Learning to hear music as sound taught me how to hear sound as music. After all, music and sound are not separate realms, and neither are the concert hall and the city streets. It is all part of one single sonic environment that our ears inhabit. So the next time you are in the mood for music, try something new; maybe put on Kind of Blue. If you are feeling adventurous the next time you are out and about, try listening to the world as a recording studio full of new and experimental sounds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Look at Snow]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/12/how-to-look-at-snow/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/12/how-to-look-at-snow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><em>This piece is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lipogram">lipogram</a> in which I did not use the letter E (do a Ctrl-F if you don’t believe me). It was immensely challenging, but I had a fun time writing it. Enjoy.</em></p>

<p> 
Nothing can approach that first sighting of snow falling softly from a calm gray sky. Racing to my window and taking a good long look, visions of snowballs and toboggans and igloos flash through my mind. I am struck by a familiar youthful thrill. But I also think of walking through snowy woods. So I grab my stuff and go out.</p>

<p>Road lamps cast a glow, gold light diffusing warmly against a dark bluish background. Distant things sound faint. My boots crunch. Pausing, I pick up a soft but distinct sound, hard to put into words. Possibly how a thousand tiny crystal shards would sound colliding — a soothing, glassy tingling, akin to rhythmic rain. Withdrawn into isolation, I walk, not minding how cold it is. Soon, though, it turns into a raging blizzard of furious winds and blinding snow. I hurry back and as I rush in, I am struck by a familiar air: an aroma of smoky wood, a crackling of burning logs. Only during a snowstorm is this so inviting. A cup of hot cocoa awaits and I top it off with big marshmallows.</p>

<p>Sipping, I watch as snow’s sublimity transforms my world; all physical flaws vanish — no footprints, no sign of dirt; only a minimalistic fantasy. A blank canvas, full of possibility. And this, I think, is how all should look at snow.</p>

<p>But most don’t look at it this way. To many, snow is that awful stuff that sticks to scarfs and hats and hair, that stings skin, that drifts and blows around annoyingly; a cold dust that afflicts us in months around January. Moms and dads and various adults moan about how snow ruins roads, forming hazardous traps that all of us must unavoidably confront. Driving to work or school, typically quotidian, turns into an awful affair — traffic, plow trucks, and a slurry of salt, slush, and snow. Catching such words, I always think, <em>How sad, to think if that’s all snow is.</em> Having grown up in a Boston suburb, I’m fairly familiar with all things having to do with snow. Snow practically accounts for half of my childhood joy, a joy that I will not outgrow. So, naturally, I think that a man who knows only how to complain about snow is dogmatic and lacks a youthful outlook that savors snow for its fun and its bright and shining charm. Such a man is missing out on what’s important about snow — its magic. And that day that my school was caught amidst an abrupt snowstorm was nothing short of magical.</p>

<p>What a vivid sight — gothic archways, courtyards normally grassy, and old oaks showcasing a grand snowy cap. At midnight, vast crowds flock to Old Campus, lit by lamplight. Small groups form and soon, total chaos bursts out. A thousand kids frolic in snow on a Monday night, choosing fun and punting work. Snowballs fly this way and that. Occasionally, amidst raucous laughs and joyous shouts, a satisfying thud sounds; a good shot found its mark.</p>

<p>Panting, I go back to my dorm, worn out by our wintry fight. Collapsing on my chair, blood still pumping fast, I look out of my window, gazing out at snow dancing around a lamplight’s halo. I am calm again, happy, and I think: <em>Thank god for snow.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asking the Difficult Question]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/12/asking-the-difficult-question/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/12/asking-the-difficult-question</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>They bombarded us with warnings about the consequences of irresponsible drinking even before I got to college. The high school principal, teachers, and guidance counselors wanted us to understand that binge drinking is a serious matter — it leads to deaths. When I arrived at Yale, freshman counselors, college deans, and parents sternly reminded us of the same message. This time, they also talked about sexual health and the importance of verbal consent.</p>

<p>Of course, none of this surprised me. Clearly there is a growing awareness about the dangers associated with college-style drinking and hostile sexual climates. Last year, I read an article in Rolling Stone that was referred to me by my brother, friends, and websites like Reddit.com. It was about one student’s account of how Dartmouth’s frat culture dehumanizes their pledges. I googled around, wondering how credible the story was since it described things that seemed too gruesome to be true (stuff involving vomit and various other human wastes). One related article linked me to another and soon I found myself with a mess of tabs open in my browser, each with a story and an opinion about the shortcomings of college culture. The discussion was fierce, opinions were expressed through bold rhetoric and provocative claims. I discovered a scandal that occurred only two years ago at the college I was preparing to attend: pledges of the Yale fraternity Delta Kappa Epsilon, known as DKE, had chanted misogynistic slurs outside the Women’s Center. I spent that entire night going through a torrent of news reports, blog posts, and opinion editorials; some of them commented on campus culture, some of them denounced the Yale administration. Long threads of comments trailed each article, not just the casual musings of regular readers or the deliberately offensive statements of internet trolls, but substantial comments by people who cared about the issue. All of this sparked by one incident? Unlikely — this was definitely not just a passing concern, not just one of those controversies that inexplicably comes and goes. Behind this single Yale scandal was a fierce, ongoing debate about a serious problem in college culture.</p>

<p>I was amazed that nobody brought this up; not my freshman counselor, not my college dean, not the president of Yale. Not even in the context of talking about sexual safety did they mention anything about the DKE scandal that occurred only two years ago. Instead, to justify their grave warnings, they said, “it’s for your safety.” Drinking is bad because it has immediate dangers associated with it: it can lead to inappropriate sexual activity, it can leave someone physically vulnerable in a dangerous situation, drinking too much poisons the body. Lack of sexual consent is bad because someone’s emotional and physical safety is violated when he or she is pressured into unwanted sexual activity. Not to mention, both are illegal.</p>

<p>Yes, safety is an important consideration, but is that all that is important? While I acknowledge that this is a legitimate concern, I am not just interested in what is safe; I am interested in what is moral — in what is right. Why, during orientation, did nobody approached the issues of drinking and sex from the ethical lens I had encountered in the online articles? I can understand why counselors and deans would refrain from offering these views; the matter gets to be intimately personal, inevitably leading to discussions of individual values and such. But why did these mentor figures, meant to guide us through our first days of college, pretend that drinking and sex is only an issue when physical and emotional safety is concerned? From what I read in the articles and comments, the scandal didn’t stir up the greater community so aggressively because someone might have gotten emotionally or physically hurt; the event was so controversial because a group of Yale students came together and collectively did something so obviously immoral. Not one of the participants paused to think about what they were saying, why they were saying it, and whom they were saying it to. This is what disturbs me the most — that it was a real example of the herd mentality authors like Orwell, Huxley, and Bradbury warned us about.</p>

<p>The morality of college-style drinking and sex needs to be discussed in a more open and purposeful manner. Many of the authors of the blogs and articles I read were students of Yale College with distinctive voices, whose contributions fueled the discussion. So why should it be any different in the common room, the dining hall, or the courtyard? Oftentimes in casual conversations, students will shy away from critically examining college students’ attitudes towards drinking and sex, mirroring the way Yale mentors avoided the question. They avoid questions like, Why are binge-drinking and the one night stand glorified? Should they be glorified? I take it that in general, people are afraid to critique the accepted ethical norms for fear of making moral judgments on individuals. But mute acceptance of the popular attitudes is itself a moral judgment because without criticism, the social atmosphere can begin to impose the very moral pressures people try to prevent. Furthermore, our ethical choices affect our personal lives in significant ways that extend beyond just the realm of safety. Ethical choices can also profoundly affect our happiness and our personal growth. Given the stakes, I don’t think ubiquity is a reason to assume that the given standards are right and more importantly, it is not a reason to assume that the standards are universally accepted and that conversation is unnecessary. Clearly not everybody agrees with the stereotypical college party mentality. Individuals are the ones disagreeing and starting the conversation in the first place.</p>

<p>The larger and more essential question is this: what do I as an individual think about the morality of the behavior around me? The DKE incident happened because individuals each made a decision to participate, whether consciously or unconsciously. A community’s ethical norms rest on individual values and decisions, so in questioning the ethics, it would make sense to also question personal values, those both of oneself and of others. The platitude, “Don’t judge,” warns us to avoid attacking others’ personal values and it is often the response I get when I start challenging the glorification of binge-drinking and the “hook up” culture. The phrase is an easy out for those who confuse honest discussion with dogmatic assertion, for those who fear confronting the difficult yet important topics that loom close to personal values. People can’t stand to face questions like, “Why do some college students choose to get drunk and suffer a hangover repeatedly?” “Why are one-night stands in which the two partners never speak to each other again considered worthwhile?” When I or others pose these questions, we are not declaring our moral superiority. Rather, we are looking for honest discussion about a subject that matters to us. Of course we all hold different beliefs as to what is right and wrong, and sometimes one person’s values can directly oppose another’s in a very antagonizing and uncomfortable way. But that’s okay — the point is not to simply agree with others or reach the same conclusions. The point is to agree to have this crucial conversation, to ask the questions that matter but too often have been passed over in silence.</p>

<p>I don’t believe that wild and shameless partying is anything glorious. In fact, I have more than a few moral qualms about it and because of this, I ask questions like these: in parties, why is alcohol nicknamed the “social lubricant,” and treated as a replacement for honest conversation? Why do some people admit to using alcohol as a way to tolerate “how bad the parties are?” If the parties are that bad, why go at all? It seems that students feel obliged not only to avoid evaluating the culture, but also to participate in it. I wonder how happy they are, and I suspect that not all of them feel comfortable if some need alcohol for such reasons, in such high quantities. One Yale guest columnist writes, “Trust me: freshman year means no shame. To the contrary—you will cherish your poor choices. You will delight to see that hook-up—whom you will not acknowledge—eating in your dining hall.” From the freshmen I’ve met so far, I don’t think most of us intend to treat our first year at Yale as a chance to recklessly indulge ourselves, to “cherish” mistakes because “freshman year means no shame.” So why aren’t more students advocating alternatives to this reckless, shameless attitude? My friend offered this explanation: people engage in the popular college culture because it feels liberating to do something traditionally considered taboo. But then again, I’m not satisfied with this answer. I think there’s something else motivating this unrestrained, unashamed behavior. Personally, I suspect that it has something to do with a lack of careful thought about one’s choices. I don’t think most college students are rational hedonists who consume dangerous amounts of liquor and wake up in strangers’ beds after thinking it through with reason, concluding that this was in their best interest.</p>

<p>One way to rephrase the difficult question is: What do I really want? Fondly called the “bright college years,” we are told by older folk that college is a time to find ourselves, to discover more about our own identities. It is also a time to continue creating ourselves. I intend to do just that by forming my own opinions and voicing them with an ear to what others have to say. I will either agree or disagree with the views of popular culture, but always with my own reasons, always with an evaluative focus. But most importantly, I hope to inform and possibly amend my personal moral values by the wide variety of perspectives I will encounter in honest discussions and hopefully, in honest behavior.</p>

<p>And I will always be asking myself, What do I think is right?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Little Things]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/11/the-little-things/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/11/the-little-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>            About to board the plane, I checked my bag for my laptop and passport. Caitlin checked for her stuffed animal—an odd-looking, brown creature called “Domo”—neglecting, among other valuables, an Apple laptop, expensive souvenirs from China, and her family heirloom ring. Teasingly I shook my head and asked, “What would you do if the Domo wasn’t there?” She looked me in the eyes with an expression of terror, deliberately dramatic but also, I think, partly sincere. “I would start bawling like a baby.” she replied. To anyone who doesn’t know her, it would seem odd that she, a college student, considers a child’s toy her most valuable possession. It would seem even more odd that she falls asleep every night clutching Domo to her chest. “He’s cozy and reminds me of home,” she would say so matter-of-factly, as if no further justification were needed.</p>

<p>This isn’t her only childlike idiosyncrasy.</p>

<p>In high school we would often go on walks after school and on the weekends, strolling through the center of town and the local parks. Anytime she caught sight of a dog, she would point and exclaim, “Doggie!” Whenever we passed an ice-cream shop, she would improvise some excuse and moments later I would find us sharing an ice cream cone stacked to the brim.</p>

<p>She was a mystery I couldn’t quite figure out. I knew she behaved this way partly to amuse me and partly because she liked being silly. But there was something else to her youthfully capricious behavior, an element of sincerity that couldn’t be feigned. I found myself wondering if part of her defied growing up and chose instead to remain as a child, unabashed and uninhibited.</p>

<p>She certainly possesses the honesty and spontaneity of someone much younger. Consider me for contrast: I am an incessant planner driven by purpose, someone who feels compelled to organize even the leisure activities of a lazy Sunday afternoon: go to the library from one to two, walk around the Town Hall from two to three, go home and read from three to five. Caitlin, on the other hand, prefers to go where whim and circumstance take her. She would take me on walks without a destination, content to aimlessly wander the suburban roads and woodsy trails. As we treaded into the unfamiliar, I would grow uncomfortable, wanting to stop and figure out where we were. Looking over at her, I would see only a pair of curious, light-brown eyes. “I love wandering and seeing where I end up,” she would say. One time the path took us to a tall deserted bridge that passed over a wide marsh. It was rusted and covered in what looked like years of graffiti—thick lines of color overlapping to create a fluorescent chaos. Another time the path took us to a miniature peninsula that jutted out into a lake. There we found a forgotten bench, where we spent an afternoon talking and daydreaming the hours away. <em>So this is what can happen without a plan,</em> I thought<em>. So this is what it means to adventure</em>.</p>

<p>With Caitlin, rain was no longer an inconvenience; it was an invitation to go outside and see the world in gray and silver. Getting lost was no longer an accident; it was a chance to discover something new, to stumble upon a delightful surprise.</p>

<p>It still surprises me that we ended up together despite our opposing personalities—I always wanting to determine something’s deeper meaning, she able to appreciate it for what it simply <em>is</em>. And this quality, though I associate it with her youthful side, gives her unique insight in understanding her friends and family. Sometimes her mother would come home from a long day of work, mentally exhausted and emotionally frustrated. With a pained sigh and an attempt to seem happy, her mother would say, “Hi dear, how was school?” Sensing that her mom was silently being overwhelmed by a torrent of stressful thoughts about how terrible the day was, Caitlin would sit her down and bring her a cup of hot tea. “Let’s watch a crappy movie tonight. I’ll run to CVS and pick up some popcorn and gummy worms,” she would say. She knew her mother too well.</p>

<p>Caitlin makes it easy to appreciate those small things that inevitably escape one’s notice on any given day, dwarfed by bigger, more pressing matters. She inspires joy even in the most difficult circumstances. When I left for college, she gave me a jar filled with hundreds of colorful paper slips, each with a little note. She wrote, “Here’s a jar of random thoughts. Pull one out to make you smile when you miss me.” I remember a few long nights when I could do nothing but lie in my bed and feel the weight of her absence. I would pull out some paper slips from her jar, not expecting anything to bring me out of my misery, especially not words on pieces of paper. But of course, she knew exactly what to say.</p>

<p>“Take a break from the textbooks and go for a walk.”</p>

<p>“Don’t forget to add to our bucket list, we need awesome ideas.”</p>

<p>“When you’re feeling down, play some Frank Sinatra to remind yourself that you’re classy.”</p>

<p>Sometime later, Caitlin mailed me a copy of <em>The Little Prince</em>. Sitting in a quiet courtyard one afternoon, I put aside the Nietzsche tome (what I was reading for leisure at the time) and read this children’s book instead. The story about a prince from a tiny planet and his journey through the stars refreshed me, more than Nietzsche would have. I especially enjoyed the cartoonish watercolor illustrations.</p>

<p>A handkerchief hangs by her bedside that reads, “Life is short. Enjoy the little things.” But despite her eye for the little things, she is also vulnerable to big things. The day Caitlin received news that her Aunt’s cancer was getting worse, a glossy, unfocused look replaced her charming smile; blankness took the place of the subtle yet charismatic smile that always lingered on the corners of her mouth and the tops of her cheeks. She grew quiet, preferring neither to speak nor to listen. She passed by dogs and ice cream stores without expression, and when I pointed them out trying to cheer her up, she would only smile weakly. “What do you want to do today?” I asked. “I don’t know, I’m fine with anything,” she replied automatically. After several such instances, I realized that just as her mood can be lifted by the world, it can also be dragged down. Since the world doesn’t always present itself in an uplifting light, her spontaneous personality comes at a cost. And even when happy moments occur, they are, after all, only “little things.” A stuffed animal cannot possibly comfort her for the fact that her aunt has cancer.</p>

<p>Even when Caitlin retreats from the world into an inner melancholia, I want to believe that her lively side hasn’t disappeared, but that it has only been overshadowed. The problem is, nobody—not her family, not her friends, not I—can bring her out of those moods the way she can for others. None of us seem to have Caitlin’s youthful spirit that lets us see and express how comforting a stuffed animal, how delicious an ice cream cone, or how utterly exciting a dog can be. So we end up feeling helpless, able to sympathize with her but unable to console her.</p>

<p>Recently Caitlin had been buried by an enormous workload (typical for students of MIT), and was having trouble sleeping. Try as I might, my words had not been able to reassure her that things would turn out okay. But this afternoon, she sounded different when I called. I could once again hear signs of the characteristic energy; she spoke faster, with a certain lilt. Every so often she laughed. Caitlin described her first tutoring session that afternoon. “Since it was the first day, we went to a playground and played together so my kid could get to know me. She’s seven years old and so cute!” She talked about all the adorable things her kid did and said and how happy it made her. She sounded like herself. Perhaps no one can animate her spirit like a child can. Perhaps, just as Caitlin reminds us what it’s like to be young at heart, children remind her of the same. “My kid was so honest and enthusiastic, so much more than adults.”</p>

<p>As I’m writing this, trying to sort out all my memories and thoughts in an attempt to produce a cohesive and complete depiction of her, one memory keeps recurring. It’s February. Snow covers the ground—the kind that forms a week after a snowstorm, shining brightly under the sun and crunching underneath boots. We’re on vacation with a couple of friends, planning to spend four nights at a quaint rental home in Vermont’s countryside. Rolling hills, small dirt roads, and colonial houses dot the landscape. Besides the occasional smoke rising from a chimney and the infrequent passing of a car, things are still and quiet. Things could not be more idyllic. One night we build a fire in the backyard. Nestled beneath many layers of clothing, we sit close to the burning logs. After a short while our friends go inside, preferring the couch and TV. Caitlin and I stay outside, enjoying the fire’s dancing light, inviting warmth, and rustic smell. We sit there without speaking, content to gaze into the flames and listen to the crackling. I look over at her, about to ask if she wants to head in, but I stop. She looks mesmerized by the fire, her eyes holding that distinct brightness, but more intense, and accentuated by the reflection of the flames. She snuggles against me and tears roll down her cheeks.</p>

<p>“This is so perfect,” she says.</p>

<p>I feel a twinge of discomfort because I know she will lose this feeling once we go back home.</p>

<p>This same feeling translates into worry as I think about Caitlin in the context of college. During her time at MIT, she, like all college students, will have to face unavoidable questions about her future — an abstraction that becomes real in the form of majors and internships and financial independence. The same emotional sensitivity that allows her to delight in the little things makes her especially vulnerable to the practical matters that feel much more significant. She will certainly have to give up much of the time she would have spent getting lost on long walks and rejoicing in rainy days. But, being in an environment meant to transform students into full-fledged adults, will she have to give up her youthful spirit? I worry about whether or not this part of her is being diminished. I worry about how happy she is. I worry about how hard it is for Caitlin to be herself.</p>

<p>But then she sends me a handwritten letter of elegantly rounded letters occasionally punctuated by endearing smiley faces, and I am reminded that she is still the same Caitlin. Then she visits me and I see the same pair of light-brown eyes and the same rosy cheeks raised in anticipation of a smile. And somehow, in that moment, I am convinced that college cannot take this away from her, this defiantly youthful spirit that is essential to her very nature. I can imagine seeing her in four years, more mature and independent by anyone’s standards, but still the same girl at heart.</p>

<p>“This is so perfect,” she would say again, as someone able to see the world through the eyes of youth; someone for whom the delight of Domo and dogs and winter fires is simply too valuable to give up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Without Words]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2012/10/without-words/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2012/10/without-words</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><em>The following is meant to be an addendum to my previously posted essay, “The Woods and I, and Her.” A lipogram is a form of writing in which a certain letter or group of letters is suppressed. In this case, I suppressed the letter E. Writing it was enjoyable—for the first ten hours or so.</em></p>

<p>I was amidst autumn’s full glory. During a gradual transition in my town’s visual backdrop, that distinctly rich viridian color of spring was transforming into a brilliant gold. Fall, an annual occasion promising natural and satisfying tranquility, spurs my mind to think in privacy. But this fall I was always with Caitlin, walking on trails winding through woods and parks. Writing this stirs up nostalgia, for I miss my town’s distinct, idyllic charm. No, that’s not it. I miss that girl who I can talk to without words. I miss sitting on that wood platform with Caitlin, hand in hand, taking in a calmly flowing brook’s bubbling sounds. In Caitlin’s company, words can act as linguistic masks, trivial sounds, falling unsatisfyingly far from truth. In such situations, which almost always occur following instants of surprising bliss, words simply fail. For all I know, I could just lack a good vocabulary. But also, such thoughts thwart a logical, syntactical organization. Anyways, Caitlin and I could pass long durations without talking, that which I could not possibly do individually. Again and again I saw how wrong I was about joys of privacy and isolation. Without Caitlin, autumn would lack that particular quality so captivating that I can savor it still, as I am writing. I could say similar things about any month, any day, any hour that I was with my girl.</p>

<p>My journal, which usually lay in dust, ran into gradually rising amounts of ink—a runoff of thoughts that my mind could not contain. I saw its transformation into a bank of autobiographical narrations and individual ruminations. Flipping through my journal, I know that words, again, fail; all words that is, but this singular “Caitlin.”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
